<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A catechisme, that is to saie, a familiar introduccion and trainyng of the simple in the commaundementes of God, and the principles of oure religion muche necessarie to be taught and knowen to all good christian people, sette foorth in questions with direct answers to the same: [et] translated into Englishe for the behoufe and commoditee not onely of childre[n], but also of al suche deuout lerners as are not seen in the Latine toungue.</title>
            <author>Allen, Edmund, 1519?-1559.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 101 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16684</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 359</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104375</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840113</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840113</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4584</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16684)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4584)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 517:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A catechisme, that is to saie, a familiar introduccion and trainyng of the simple in the commaundementes of God, and the principles of oure religion muche necessarie to be taught and knowen to all good christian people, sette foorth in questions with direct answers to the same: [et] translated into Englishe for the behoufe and commoditee not onely of childre[n], but also of al suche deuout lerners as are not seen in the Latine toungue.</title>
                  <author>Allen, Edmund, 1519?-1559.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[200] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Fletestrete at the signe of the Sunne ouer against the conduyte, by Edwarde Whitchurche,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at Londo[n] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>The. xix. daye of October the yere of our Lorde. M.D.XLVIII. [1548]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Edmund Allen, whose name appears at the beginning of the preface.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-M N⁴.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4584:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4584:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A catechiſme,</hi> that is to ſaie, a familiar introduccion and trainyng of the ſimple in the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of God, and the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of oure religion, muche neceſſarie to be taught and knowen to all good chriſtian people, ſette foorth in queſtions with direct anſwers to the ſame: &amp; tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into Engliſhe for the behoufe and commoditee not onely of childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but alſo of al ſuche de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners as are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Latine toungue.</p>
            <q>Suffre the litle children to come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, for theirs is the kyngdome of God. <bibl>Marc. x.</bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:4584:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4584:2"/>
            <head>¶ Vnto the faythfull chriſtian flocke and congregaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Ieſus Chriſte, Edmonde Alen wiſheth, grace, peace, and mercye from God our heauenly father, through our ſauior Ieſus Chriſte.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye and mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God our heauenlye, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, &amp; moſte deare father, moniſheth and warneth vs (ye dearely beloued in our ſauior Chriſt) both by worde and alſo by diuerſe exaumples, that we all ſhould take earneſte care &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>row for our youth, that it be we inſtructe and brought vp in the true feare of God, &amp; after
<pb facs="tcp:4584:3"/> ſuche a godly ſorte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it myght liue in all vertue, godlynes &amp; honeſtie. And it is a thyng whereunto not onely the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the heathen, but alſo our owne naturall reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly experience, &amp; the loue of the comon wealth ought lawfully to moue and enforce vs. For aſmuche as we dayly fele and perceiue right euidently, what inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce doth inſue, where youth is neglecte &amp; not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And agayne what a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, comfort &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie it is vnto an whole comon wealth, where youth is well brought vp in godly learnyng &amp; exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and exerciſed in vertue &amp; holyneſſe. This I ſaye, myght be ſufficient to ſtyrre vp and to kindle our heartes toward the
<pb facs="tcp:4584:3"/> right inſtitucion &amp; bryngyng vp of youth, although we wer but very heathen. But foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as we are chriſtian men and women, and through out ſauior Chriſt become the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, therfore the moſt holy worde of God &amp; the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of our ſauior Chriſt, ought moſte ſpecially to allure &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke vs vnto this moſte holy and neceſſary office. For fyrſt it is euident ynough by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſtes what an high charge our ſauior Chriſte geueth vs ouer youth. Math. xviii. &amp; .xix. and Marke. x. Where, by his hertye and louyng imbracyng of them, he declareth manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that no ſeruice can bee more acceptable vnto him, than that whiche is ſpent about them, to
<pb facs="tcp:4584:4"/> bryng and induce them vnto him. Lykewyſe howe earneſtly doeth S. Paul commaund all parentes to bryng vppe theyr children in nurture and exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion? Ephe. vi. and Collo. iii. For the whiche cauſe, all chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren haue a ſpeciall commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God to be obedience vnto theyr fathers &amp; mothers, becauſe they ought to be vnto them, as the very deputies and officers of God, in continually exerciſyng them to the glorye and honor of God. And howe highly almyghtie God regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the ryght inſtitucion of youth, we may learne out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old teſtamente ſufficiently, and ſpecially out of the .xviii cha. of Geneſis. Wheras God, ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng vnto the faythfull Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham
<pb facs="tcp:4584:4"/> his mynde and purpoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte Sodoma &amp; Gomorra ſayeth theſe woordes. <hi>I knowe, ſayeth the Lorde, that his children ſhall kepe the wayes of the Lorde, and do that thyng whiche is ryght and iuſt, that the Lorde may ſuffer that thyng to come to paſſe vnto Abraham, whiche he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed hym. &amp;c.</hi> This holy ſentence of God ought to be alone ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient vnto a chriſten man (whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is by faythe a childe of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham) to moue hym to apply all indeuour and ſtudye to the chriſten educacion of youth. For here we haue a ſingulare comforte &amp; a ſure promyſe, that if we be founde true &amp; faythfull towarde theſe gyftes of God our children, than wyll God daily encreaſe &amp; augmente hys grace towarde vs, and enduce
<pb facs="tcp:4584:5"/> vs into further knowledge of his godly wyll, to the glory of his name, &amp; welth of our ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. And beſide this, God ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſtrayght commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by expreſſe woordes in diuerſe places that we ſhoulde in no wyſe neglecte our youth. As in the .vi. and .xi. of Deu. where God commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded Moſes that all menne ſhoulde teache theyr children and childrens children, his lawes &amp; commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. Lykewiſe, through the ꝓphete Dauid, God ſpeaketh theſe wordes in the .lxxviii. Pſalme. <hi>The lord hath made a couenaunt with Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, and hath geuen Iſrael a lawe, which their poſteritie and heires ſhould knowe, and tell it vnto their children, that they might alſo put and fixe their hope and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fidence vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, and kepe his comaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and not for get his workes. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4584:5"/>
            <p>By this we muſt nedes confeſſe and knowledge that it is an high thyng, by god our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the moſte requiſite &amp; ſpeciall poyncte in a chriſten co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacion, that the chyldren be well taught and inſtructe in the wayes of the Lorde, and in the couenaunte whiche God hath made with theyr fathers and theyr poſteritie for euer in our Sauyour Chriſte. For by this meanes only they muſt learne to knowe God, to be fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded of his mercy and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towarde them, to put all theyr truſte and confidence in him only and to loue and feare hym. And this foundation once layed, they ſhall afterwarde frame and buylde theyr whole lyfe vpon theſame, and learne
<pb facs="tcp:4584:6"/> all humblenes, obedience, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie, vertue and godlynes, in worde and dede, and dayly be more inclyned and bente to the true religion and knowlege of God, and euermore increaſe &amp; goe forwarde in theſame. And thus the whole common welth ſhall receyue comforte and ioy by them: And they in proceſſe of time, ſhall learne to inſtructe their chyldren in the Lorde, in lyke maner. And thus there ſhall neuer waxe any nettels, thiſtles or wedes in this tillage of the Lorde, nor they ſhall not periſhe through our negligence.</p>
            <p>For God ſuffereth vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in this worlde, (&amp; taketh vs not away immediatly after we haue atteyned to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of hym) for no nother
<pb facs="tcp:4584:6"/> cauſe, but that we ſhould helpe &amp; further other vnto theſame, that the glory &amp; perfite religion of God myght alſo bee planted &amp; waxe in our children &amp; poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytie. And ſurely the negligence of men in this behalfe hath hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been the chefe cauſe of ſo many and dyuers heuy pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues of God. As Chriſte doeth manyfeſtlye declare where he ſayth: <hi>Woo vnto hym that offendeth</hi> (or hindreth) <hi>youth. &amp;c. It were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he wer caſt into the ſea with a mylſtone about his necke and drowned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherfore all they that wyll auoyde this woe, let them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply all that ſtudy and care with moſt earneſt zeale and indeuor, that their youth be wel inſtruct and brought vp.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4584:7"/>
            <p>For this can no man denye, that the very occaſion and grounde of all the miſchiefe and wycked diſſolutenes that reigneth in the worlde at this daye, is, that the bringing vp of youth is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nor diligenter regarded. Where ſubiectes are not ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient vnto their heades and rulers as they ought to be, it is moſte ſpecially in ſuche places where the inſtitucion of youth hath been neglecte. Likewiſe where parentes are vnreuerent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly intreated of their children, it is through the ſufferaunce of God for a puniſhemente vnto them for ſo euill and negligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brynging of them vp in theyr youth. And what hath been the cauſe of the heuy blindneſſe and ignoraunce in the worlde, in the
<pb facs="tcp:4584:7"/> trwe relygion and ſeruice of God, of the manifold ydolatry &amp; ſuperſticion, other than the lacke of the ryght &amp; true inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tucion of youth? Wherfore yf we will auoyde the wrath and indignacion of God, &amp; all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er of inconuenience, let vs apply more ſtudie &amp; diligence that our youth maye be better brought vp in the knowledge and feare of God, that in theyr younge and tender age they maye learne the prynciples of Chriſtes religion and of our chriſten fayth. Which ſhalbe a meane to a voyde all the inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce aboue reherſed. And if we do not this, let vs loke for no nother but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr bloude, periſſhing through our negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, ſhall be ſtraitly requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of our handes. And not
<pb facs="tcp:4584:8"/> onely of parentes, but alſo of all ſuche as haue any cure and charge of youth, as Schole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters in theyr ſcholes, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours and miniſters in theyr cures. Theſe ſhould bee the ſpeciall inſtructours of youth. Theſe ſhoulde beate into chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens heades the chiefe poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and articles of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten doctryne. As are, the .x. Commaundementes, the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tycles of the fayth, the Lordes prayer, the inſtitucion of the holy Sacramentes of Bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſme, and of the holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lorde, and laſte of all, the inſtitucion of the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall or churche diſciplyne and exerciſe of brotherly correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4584:8"/>
            <p>Theſe poynctes beeyng fyrſte taught vnto chyldren by theyr parentes woorde for woorde, (whiche is the office and duty of all chriſten parentes to do,) a playne and ſymple vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of them, might afterward bee taught them eyther in the ſchole by the ſcholemaiſters, or els in the churche by the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoures and miniſters, geuyng them euery Sunday one ſhorte article or queſtion to learne, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petyng it diſtinctlye twyſe or thryſe, and requiring it of them agayne the nexte Sunday, and than to gyue and repete vnto them in lyke maner another, vntyll the whole Catechiſme, be learned out, and than begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng agayne.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4584:9"/>
            <p>If but one houre were thus ſpente euery Sonday of euery paſtour and miniſter in exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the youthe in the churche before the face of the whole pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhe, or of euery ſcholemaiſter but once a weke, (theyr paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes earneſtly warning and dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng theim to learne and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre what is taught them) we ſhoulde fele w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in one yeare, what infinite profite ſhoulde come thereof, and within fewe yeares we ſhoulde haue a flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhing common welth: This doeth God moſte ſtraytely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of vs, and we had neuer ſuche occaſion vnto it as we nowe haue, conſideryng howe earneſtly our moſte chriſten ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, the Kynges moſte excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maieſtie, his ryght woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb facs="tcp:4584:9"/> &amp; noble counſailour, gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour of his graces perſon, the lorde Protectors grace, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his graces moſt chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> councell, do intende and mynde the true plantyng and ſettyng foorth of Chriſtes pure religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this realme. Whoſe fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uente and moſte chriſtian zeale, if we ſhould not withall pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and thankefulnes receyue, we ſhould ſhewe and proue our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues no true naturall ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Lette euery one therfore, moſte faythfull chriſtians, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply his faythfull ſtudie and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuor to further and helpe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde theyr gracious prynces moſte godly trauaile and proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges in the kingdome of god. So ſhall it in ſhort ſpace floriſh among vs. And we ſhall feele
<pb facs="tcp:4584:10"/> God to be our mercyfull, father indewyng vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull grace againſte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſautes of all our enemies: And that men might haue ſome forme &amp; trade to inſtructe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> youth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, I haue gathered out of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers lerned &amp; chriſtian wryters of Cathechiſmes, this briefe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruccion, in ſuche queſtions as ſemed vnto me moſte neceſſary for children to learne. Wherof they may learne euery weke one (beyng ſo repeted as is aboue wryten) without any difficultie at all. This I ſubmit vnto the iudgement of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faythfull what ſoeuer they be, deſiring all men to interprete my faythfull inde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uor therein to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt, and to vſe it ſo far as they may haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte and edification therby.
<pb facs="tcp:4584:10"/> Almyghtie God geue all men generally grace to ſeke erneſtly the furtheraunce of his kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the youth. And ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally God geue all parentes and paſtours whiche haue ſpeciall charge and cure of youth, grace to inſtructe and bryng them vp in his feare, as may be moſte to the glory &amp; honor of his name. God geue alſo all chyldren and youth his holy ſpirite, that they may receyue all godly &amp; vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous doctryne &amp; enſample, that they maye become the very ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes and children of God, &amp; after this lyfe with their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, maye enioy the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite ſight and fruicion of their heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:4584:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4584:11"/>
            <head>A chriſtian introductio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for youth co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ing the prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciples of our fayth &amp; religion. The maſter axeth the queſtion according as he hath taught all thynges to the ſcholer afore. The ſcholer aunſwereth as he hath afore learned and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued it of the maiſter.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Maiſter.</speaker>
               <p>SPeake my louyng chylde, what art thou?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The ſcholer.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, accordyng vnto my firſte birth I am a creature of God indued with vnderſtandyng &amp; reaſon, but yet borne in ſynne, and therfore of no value.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>How and to what end hath God created the?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Whan I was nothyng, he
<pb facs="tcp:4584:12"/> of his exceding grace and mere goodneſſe created me, that I might perfitely lerne to knowe hym, to loue him, to feare hym, to laude and to prayſe him, and finally to be partaker of all his ineſtimable riches &amp; benefites.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>How hath God created the?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt he hath made me a body out of the yerth, and furnyſhed the ſame withall neceſſary lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes &amp; members. Than hath he indued the ſame bodye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, liuely, and an immortall ſoule, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after his own image, by reaſon whereof I am, as it were, a liuely image of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But howe can the image of God be reſembled in man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>For ſouth thus: as God is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyng and immortall, euen ſo is the ſoule of man alſo. And
<pb facs="tcp:4584:12"/> againe, lyke as God is the lorde of all creatures, ſo hath he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained man to be lorde ouer all bodily creatures, &amp; hath made them all to be ſubiect vnto hym and to ſerue him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Is not the image of God righteouſnes, holynes, trueth, euerlaſtyng ioy and ſaluation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yes for ſouth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Howe canſt thou than be a ſynner and of no value?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>I haue inherited ſynne of Adam the firſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that was created.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Was Adam than a ſynner?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>God created hym after his owne image, ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, good and holy, and gaue hym a commaundement, not to eate of the fruite of knowlage of good and euill, whiche com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente yf he had obſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued and kept, he &amp; all his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
<pb facs="tcp:4584:13"/> ſhould haue remayned holy and bliſſed for euer. But he tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed that commaundement, perſuaded by decipteful inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and prouocacion of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and ſo he became a ſinner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But what maketh that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte the? Art thou a ſynner becauſe Adam was a ſynner? or through Adams traſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Foraſmuche as he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed God, therfore dyd God punyſhe hym withall his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, ſo that euer ſynce that fall of Adam both he and we all are depriued &amp; ſpoyled of the image of God, and ſo are borne into the worlde euen from our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe, ſinners, vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and children of wrathe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Than canſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> not be ſaued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>After my fyrſt byrth, I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not
<pb facs="tcp:4584:13"/> be ſaued, but through my ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de byrth in Chriſte I haue an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted hope and aſſured truſt to be ſaued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What art thou than after thy ſeconde byrth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>I am a chriſtian.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is a Chriſtian?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>A Chriſtian is one that acknowlegeth himſelfe a ſynner, and beleueth ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that God our heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father is mercyfull vnto hym, through the gloryous paſſion and bloud ſheddyng of our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Whereby knoweſt thou, that thou art a Chriſtian?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe I doe faythfully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue the ſame, and vpon this belefe am baptyſed or chryſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the name of the father, of the ſonne, and of the holye ghoſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What belieueſt thou
<pb facs="tcp:4584:14"/> of the father, of the ſonne, and the holy ghoſte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>I beleue that the father is God, the ſonne is God, the holy ghoſte is God, and yet as theſe are three de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtincte perſones eguall in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce, glorye and maieſtie, ſo is he but onely one God eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall without begynnyng, euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng without ende, almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and altogether bounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, good, mercyfull, louyng, tendre &amp; beneficiall vnto man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What dooeſt thou ferther beleue of theſame God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the ſonne, and the holy ghoſte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>I dooe firmely and ſtedfaſtely beleue whatſoeuer is wrytten of God in the holy ſcriptures, and all that euer is conteyned in the ſpeciall poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and artycles of the chryſten
<pb facs="tcp:4584:14"/> religion, whiche the lorde hym ſelfe taught vs, and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his dyſciples to teache the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What are the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all pointes of the chriſten religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and howe many are they?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>They are ſyxe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>which ſyxe be they?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The fyrſt is the .x. commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes.</p>
               <p n="2">ii. The artycles of the holy chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian fayth.</p>
               <p n="3">iii. The holy prayer of the Lorde.</p>
               <p n="4">iiii. The woordes and inſtituci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the holy baptiſme.</p>
               <p n="5">v. The woordes of the holy ſupper of the Lorde.</p>
               <p n="6">vi. The woordes of the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall diſcipline and brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly correccion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Now rehearſe me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:4584:15"/> of all the ſyxe pryncypall poyntes and articles one after an other as I haue out of the places of Goddes holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture taught it vnto thee before this tyme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The .x. commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes are wrytten in the xx. chapiter of Exodus in theſe wordes.</p>
               <p n="1">i. I the lord am thy God which haue brought the out of Egipt out of the land of bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage, thou ſhalt haue none other Goddes beſyde me, or in my ſyght.</p>
               <p n="2">ii. Thou ſhalt make to thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe no grauen ymage, nor ſymylitude of any thyng that is in heauen aboue, or in the earth beneth, or in the waters vnder the earth, thou ſhalt ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bowe thee downe before them, nor ſhewe any ſeruice or
<pb facs="tcp:4584:15"/> reuerence vnto them. For I am the lorde thy God, a ſtrong and gelous God, for I auenge the vnrighteouſneſſe of the fathers vpon the children euen vnto the thyrde and fourthe generacion of them that hate and deſpyſe me, and I ſhewe mercye euen vnto the thouſandeſt generaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them that loue me &amp; kepe my commaundementes.</p>
               <p n="3">iii. Thou ſhalt not take the name of thy lorde god in vayne.</p>
               <p>For the Lorde wyll not ſuffer him vnpuniſhed that taketh his name in vayne.</p>
               <p n="4">iiii. Remembre that thou kepe the Sabboth daye holy. Sixe dayes ſhalte thou laboure and doe all thy buiſineſſe, but the ſeuenth daye is an holy Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both day vnto the lord thy god.
<pb facs="tcp:4584:16"/> Vpon that daye ſhalt thou doe no woorke at all, neyther thou thy ſelfe, nor thy ſonne, nor thy daughter, neyther thy manſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunte, nor thy mayd ſeruaunt, nor thy cattell, nor thy geaſt whiche kepeth or lodgeth in thy houſe. For in ſyxe dayes made the lord heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and earth, and the ſea, withal that is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but vpon the ſeuenth daye dyd he reſt from all maner of labour: therfore the lorde hath honoured and halowed the Sabboth daye.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>v.</hi> Honour thy father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that thy dayes maye bee prolonged in the lande that the Lorde thy God wyll gyue thee.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>vi.</hi> Thou ſhalt not murther.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>vii.</hi> Thou ſhalt not commit ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutry.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>viii.</hi> Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4584:16"/>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>ix.</hi> Thou ſhalt not beare falſe wytneſſe againſt thy neighbor.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>x.</hi> Thou ſhalt nor couet, nor luſt after thy neyghboures houſe, thou ſhalt not luſte after thy neybours wife, nor his ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nor his mayde, nor his oxe nor his Aſſe, nor after any thyng that is thy neybours.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="creed">
            <head>¶ The articles of the holy Chriſten feith and belefe, are theſe, and they conteyne .iii, pryncipall articles.</head>
            <p>I Beleue in God the father al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghtie maker of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and yearth.</p>
            <p>And in Ieſus Chriſt his onely ſonne our lord which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued by the holy ghoſt, borne out of the virgin Mary, ſuffred vnder Ponce Pylate, was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifyed, dyed, and was buried. Deſcended vnto the helles, and vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the thyrd day he roſe again
<pb facs="tcp:4584:17"/> from the dead, aſcended vnto the heauens and ſyttteth at the ryghthande of God the father almyghtie, from thence he ſhall come to iudge the quicke and the dead.</p>
            <p n="3">iii. I beleue in the holy ghoſt, an holy Chatholyque Churche, the communion of ſainctes, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuenes of ſynnes, the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the fleſhe, and the lyfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyng. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ The Lordes prayer wrytten in the .vi. of Matthewe and the .xi. of Luke is this.</head>
            <p>OVr father whiche arte in heauen, halowed bee thy name, thy kyngdome come, thy will be doen vpon earth as it is in heauen. Geue vs this daye our dayly bread. And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue
<pb facs="tcp:4584:17"/> vs our treſpaces, as we forgeue them that treſpace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt vs. And leade vs not in to temptacion. But deliuer vs from the euill. For thine is the kyngdome, and the power, and the glory for euer. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Scripture_passages">
            <head>¶ The woordes and inſtitucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the holy baptiſme conteyned in the newe teſtament are theſe.</head>
            <q>
               <bibl>Math. xxviii.</bibl> ANd Ieſus came &amp; ſpake vnto his dyſciples, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: All power is geuen vnto me in heauen, &amp; in yearth. Goe ye therfore, and teache all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, baptiſyng theim in the name of the father, and of the ſonne, &amp; of the holy ghoſte: tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to obſerue all thinges whatſoeuer I haue commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you. And loe I am with
<pb facs="tcp:4584:18"/> you alway euen vntyll the ende of the worlde.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Marke .xvi.</bibl> And he ſayde vnto them: Goe ye into all the worlde, &amp; preache the Goſpell to all creatures: He that beleeueth and is baptyſed ſhall be ſaued. But he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth not ſhall be damned.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Roma, vi.</bibl> Knowe ye not that all wee whiche are baptyſed in Ieſus Chriſt, are baptiſed to dye with him? We are buryed then with him by baptiſme, for to dye, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lykewyſe as Chriſt was raiſed vp frome deathe by the glorye of the Father, euen ſo wee alſo ſhoulde walke in a new lyfe.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Gala iii.</bibl>
               <p>For all ye that are baptyſed haue put on Chriſt. There is
<pb facs="tcp:4584:18"/> no Iewe, neyther gentile, there is neyther bonde, neyther free: there is neither manne nor wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For ye are all one in Chriſt Ieſus. If ye be Chriſtes, then are ye Abrahams ſede, &amp; heires according to the promiſe</p>
               <p>The places of holy ſcripture, and the woordes makyng for the inſtitucion of the Lordes ſupper are theſe here folowing.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Math. xxvi.</bibl> V<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>Han they were eatyng, Ieſus tooke breade, and whan he had geuen thankes, he brake it, and gaue it to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and ſayed: take, eate, this is my body. And he tooke the cuppe, and thanked, and gaue it them, ſaying: drynke ye all of this. For this is my bloude, whiche is of the newe teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:4584:19"/> that is ſhed for many for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſynnes.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Marke. xiiii.</bibl> And as they were eatyng, Ieſus toke bread: and whan he had geuen tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes, he brake it, and gaue to them &amp; ſayed: take, eate, this is my bodye. And he toke the cup, and whan he had geuen thankes, he toke it to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and they all dranke of it, and he ſayed vnto them: this is my bloud of the newe teſtamente, whiche is ſhed for many.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Luke. xxii.</bibl> And he toke bread, and whan he had geuen thankes, he brake it, and gaue vnto them, ſaying: this is my body, whiche is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for you. This do ye in the remembraunce of me: lykewiſe alſo, whan he had ſupped, he
<pb facs="tcp:4584:19"/> tooke the cup, ſaying: this cup is the newe Teſtamente in my bloude, whiche is ſhed for you.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. Corin. xi.</bibl>
               <p>That whiche I haue deliuered vnto you, I receiued of the lord. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord Ieſus theſame night in whiche he was betraied, toke breade: and whan he had geuen thankes, he brake it, &amp; ſaid: take ye &amp; eat, this is my body, which is broken for you This do ye in the remembraunce of me. After theſame maner alſo he toke the cuppe whan ſupper was doen, ſaying: this cuppe is the newe Teſtament in my bloude. This do as ofte as ye drinke it, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of me. For as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as ye ſhal eat this bread, and drinke of this cup, ye ſhall ſhew the lordes death till he come.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4584:20"/>
               <p>Wherfore whoſoeuer ſhal eate of this bread, or drynke of this cuppe of the lorde vnworthily, ſhall bee giltie of the bodye and bloud of the Lorde. But lette a man examine hymſelfe, and ſo lette him eate of the bread, and drynke of the cuppe.</p>
               <p>For he that eateth &amp; drynketh vnworthyly, eateth &amp; drynketh his owne damnacion, becauſe he maketh no difference of the lordes body.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="catechism">
            <head>¶The woordes of the eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall diſcipline or brotherlye correccion, are theſe.</head>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Math. xviii.</hi>
               </bibl> THe Lorde Ieſus ſayth. If thy brother ſinneth againſt thee, go thy wayes and rebuke hym betwixt the &amp; hym alone: If he heare the, than haſt thou
<pb facs="tcp:4584:20"/> wonne thy brother. If he wyll not heare the, then take one or two vnto the, that euery thyng may be at a ſtay by the mouthe of two or thre witneſſes. If he wyll not yet heare the, then tell it vnto the congregacion. If he will not heare the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacion, then take him as a heathen and as an vnchriſtian. Verely I ſay vnto you: Whatſoeuer ye ſhal bynde vpon earth, ſhal alſo be bound in heauen. And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ye ſhall leuſe vpon earth ſhall be alſo leuſed in heauen.</q>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Well, now declare me the ſame poyntes euerye one after other as I haue taught the here tofore: &amp; fyrſt tell me: why dyd God geue the .x. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes vnto man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Forſouthe to thentent we might lerne his
<pb facs="tcp:4584:21"/> will out of them,<note place="margin">Pſal. xi.</note> &amp; know what he wylleth vs to do, and what to leaue vndone.<note place="margin">Eſai. viii.</note> For the lawe of the .x. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes is a perfite rule wherby the wyll of god is knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Luke. xvi.</note> both how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue our ſelfes towardes him, our almightie euerlaſtyng god and maker, &amp; alſo towarde our neighbour and euen chriſten.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What meaneth the Lorde where he ſayeth, I am the lord thy God. &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>He wylleth that we ſhould beleue &amp; knowlege, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he of his free mercye through our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Collo. i. Gala. iiii.</note> hath redemed vs from the power of the deuill, &amp; from the bondage of the worlde and of ſynne, and hath receiued vs to be his owne peculiar, heires into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fredome &amp; felowſhip of euerlaſtyng life,
<pb facs="tcp:4584:21"/> lyke as he receyued the Iewes vnto hym,<note place="margin">Exo. xiiii.</note> whan he redeemed them out of the tirannie of the Egypcians.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And what is the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des? Thou ſhalt haue none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gods: &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>He wylleth by thoſe woordes that we ſhoulde withall diligence eſchewe and be ware of all maner of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and falſe ſeruice of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented by man, though it ſeme or be, neuer ſo high and glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is Idolatrye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Idolatrye is to haue beſydes the onely ryght god our heuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye father,<note place="margin">Eſa. xlv.</note> ſome other to ſeeke helpe at. Or Idolatrye is to make ſome other mediatour or aduocate betwene God and vs than alonely our ſauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte.<note place="margin">i. Tim. ii.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Maye we not
<pb facs="tcp:4584:22"/> than vſe the help and interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the holy Angels &amp; ſainc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, that they may make inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for vs vnto God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>We ought to ſeeke nor vſe none other meanes to obteyne the fauour of God, and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliacion of Ieſus Chriſte, than alonely ſuche as the lorde hym ſelfe hath appointed in his holy worde: but to put all our truſt and confidence in God, and in our lorde Ieſus onely, and in no creature at all</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Whan is this commaundement right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fulfilled and kept as it ought to be?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Firſte whan I beleue and doubt nothyng at all, that almightie God thorough our lorde Ieſus Chriſte, wil be my God and helper, &amp; that he will delyuer me from all euyll, and
<pb facs="tcp:4584:22"/> endue me with all felicitie both here and euerlaſtyng. Secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darily whan I put all my truſt and confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in god our heuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father, thorowe the lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte onely, truſting &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng for all help &amp; comforte, of hym alone, and of none other creature. And that thorow ſuch meanes only as he hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, forſakyng all inuencions and dreames of manne.<note place="margin">Math xv</note> Thus doyng I geue hym his Godly honor whiche is due vnto him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is mente by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond commaundement: Thou ſhalte make the no grauen I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.<note place="margin">The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> &amp;c. howe is that to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanded?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>We ought ſo to print the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of god, which is a ſpirit,<note place="margin">Iohn. v Exo. xx.</note> in our hartes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we neyther make
<pb facs="tcp:4584:23"/> nor ſette vp no maner of ymage wherunto any maner of honor or wurſhip due vnto God onlye may be geuen either outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by any geſture,<note place="margin">Deut. v. Eſa. xliiii.</note> or inwardlye in the herte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Whan is this commaundement tranſgreſſed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>As ofte as we aſcribe any diuine power vnto any ymage or ſeke any helpe at theym, or geue any manner of reuerence vnto theym, as whan we praye before them, whan we knele or fall down before them, or make curteſie vnto them, ſettyng vp any candels before theym, or cenſing them, or ſhewyng anye like poynt of reuerence: Lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe whan anye man doeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute or imagine of his owne head without any authoritie of the word of god, any maner of
<pb facs="tcp:4584:23"/> falſe ſeruice, vnder the pretence of deuocion or holynes, as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riges, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendacions, pardons, priuate ſatiſfactory maſſes for the quicke &amp; the dead, with ſuch lyke ſuperſticious goddes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice (though it hath neuer ſo high and gloryous a ſhine) yet they offende agaynſt this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why, do not all thynges pleaſe God, whiche are doen of a good mynde, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, zeale and deuocion,<note place="margin">Math. xv</note> and in the honor of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>No for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoth:<note place="margin">Deut. xii</note> for god abhorth as moſte deteſtable idolatrie, all maner of ſeruice whiche himſelfe hath not inſtituted nor commaunded in his worde: And willeth vs to flee &amp; auoyd with al our har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes all ſuche maner of ſtraunge and newe deuiſed ſeruice of our<note place="margin">Eſa. ii.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4584:24"/> owne inuentyng,<note place="margin">Ierem. vii.</note> as moſte pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilent and corrupt poyſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why hath God forbidden any reuerence to be geuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ymages?<note place="margin">Deut. v</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe that God beeyng of his owne ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce euerlaſting, immortall, incomprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſible and inuiſible, willeth that we ſhould wholly cleaue vnto his woorde,<note place="margin">Eſa. xliiii Iere. xxiii</note> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord theſame continually, both night and day bearing it about with vs in our hertes, leſt tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe any image we might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture forget him,<note place="margin">Oſee. iiii</note> or be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in his true ſeruice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What can images hindre any manne in the true ſeruice of God?<note place="margin">Heb. ii.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>There is nothyng that ſo muche withdraweth vs from the true &amp; perfecte know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege &amp; ſeruice of God, as theſe
<pb facs="tcp:4584:24"/> ſuperſticiouſe, idolatries, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.<note place="margin">Pſal. xiv Ier. xxi</note> For the only ſyght of them draweth vs from the knowlege of God. For the whiche cauſe holy ſcripture calleth theim de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyls, &amp; traps or ſnares of ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,<note place="margin">Sap. xiiii</note> &amp; the worſhippyng of them it nameth idolatry, &amp; a woorke of the fleſh.<note place="margin">Gal. v</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>May not ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges be as lay mennes bookes to put theim in remembraunce of God or of the ſayntes lyues?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Whoſoeuer ſetteth vp any image for any ſuch purpoſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly that he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied in his hert the very liuing god, &amp; is in his hert a very wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipper of idols. For the boke whiche onely can bring &amp; leade all men both laye &amp; other to the knowlege of God, is onely the worde of God conteyned in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcripture, in the byble. That
<pb facs="tcp:4584:25"/> ought to be the booke of euery laye man.<note place="margin">ii. Tim. iii. ii. Pet. i</note> For therin is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently contained all thynges ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the ſaluacion of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and it nedeth the helpe of none other booke, for it is ſufficiente of it ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Is there no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of image wherby we maye be put in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of god?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. ii</note>Yes mankynde is the lyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Image of god, made of god hymſelfe without the hande of man: Lykewiſe the heauen and yearth, the ſonne and moone, with other lyke creatures of god: Theſe may put vs dayly in remembraunce of the infinite power, goodnes, and wiſedom of God.<note place="margin">Pſal. xix Rom. i</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandyng of the thirde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement: Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lorde thy
<pb facs="tcp:4584:25"/> God in vayne. &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>In this commaundement is forbidden all maner of periury, ſweryng,<note place="margin">Math. v</note> blaſphemyng of God and his holy name.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Wherby is the name of God moſte ſpecially blaſphemed?<note place="margin">Leui. xix and .xxiiii</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>By falſe doctrine, ſuperſtici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inuocacion, or prayer, mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyng of Matyns or Euenſong (in a ſtraunge tounge) without deuocion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Whereby els?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>By falſe &amp; cuſtomable ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng, curſyng, charmyng, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuryng or inchauntyng by the name of God: alſo by any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſuperſticious vſyng the name or woorde of God, or of our ſauior Chriſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Is it a great ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne to ſweare or to curſe raſhely by the name of God, &amp; of our ſauior Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:4584:26"/> Chriſt, by his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres, workes, woundes, and bliſſed paſſion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S,</speaker>
               <p>Yea, it is ſuche an horrible, &amp; an haynous blaſphemye, that God did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde in his lawe to bee punyſhed with ſtonyng vnto death. Leui. xxiiii.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But maye a man in no caſe ſweare lawfully without offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to God?<note place="margin">Exod. xxii.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yes yf any man bee required of a magiſtrate, and other wyſe alſo yf it maye ſerue to the glory of God, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the trueth,<note place="margin">Gene. xxi.</note> or to the welth and ꝓfite of our neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the ſame.<note place="margin">ii. Ch. i</note> For by ſuche othes is the name of God ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified and not blaſphemed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kepeſt thou this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente?<note place="margin">Pſal. xlix Exod. xv.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Whanſoeuer I confeſſe, prayſe, extoll &amp; mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie his name, his wordes and
<pb facs="tcp:4584:26"/> workes in eche tyme and place as I ought to do, committyng my ſelfe wholly vnto my hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father through Ieſus Chriſte our ſauior, and callyng vpon his helpe and ayde in all maner of affliccion &amp; neceſſitie, rendryng vnto hym continuall thankes for all his benefites, &amp; auoyding all manier of thinges where through his worde, his workyng, or his glorye might in any wiſe be hindred, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or diminiſhed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>How vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſt thou the fowerth commaundement.<note place="margin">The .iiii. commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demente.</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre that thou ſanctifie the ſabboth daye. &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Lyke as there are two maner of ſabbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, a ſpirituall &amp; an exteriour ſabboth: ſo likewyſe is the ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both kept or broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two maner
<pb facs="tcp:4584:27"/> of wayes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What requireth the ſpirituall ſabboth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>That we ſhould continually mortifie, tame, &amp; crucifie our fleſhe, with all the luſtes and concupiſcence therof, and haue our continuall meditacion vpon the kyngdom of God, &amp; that we ſhould praiſe and thanke hym, aſwell in proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritye as in aduerſitye, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all manier of affliccion pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently: And whanſoeuer we do the contrarye, than breake we this ſabboth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And whan is the exteriour or outwarde ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both kept?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Whan euery man applyeth himſelfe to come vnto the churche and congregacion to heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god where it is preached, &amp; to be preſent at the common prayers, endeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng hymſelfe to pray with the
<pb facs="tcp:4584:27"/> faythfull congregacion, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes with theſame, accordyng vnto the inſtitucion and ordinaunces of Chriſte, and alſo to bryng and geue his almes in the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion for the ſuccour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of the poore. And ſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme and ſtrengthen his owne faythe, and to geue a good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of vertue vnto others. And that we myght the more quietly perfourme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ſame with out any let or hinderau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth that neither our ſeruauntes, catell, nor no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng about vs ſhould do any labor vpon that daye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Not as though it were ſynne to doe any honeſt labour (for labour is commaunded of God) or as though it were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſyng<note place="margin">Gene iii. Ephe. iiii</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4584:28"/> to God that we helpe our ſelfe or ſuccour our neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in tyme of nede, but that we myght bee more quiet to ſerue God, &amp; that our children &amp; houſeholde myght haue ſome tyme to here &amp; learne the worde of God, to remembre &amp; conſidre his benefites, to inuocate and to call vpon hym, to laude and to thanke hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And ought a man to doe no ſpeciall labour vpon that day?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>No, not for any couetouſnes of worldely encreace or aduauntage, or for any pryuate pleaſure or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, nor excepte it be eyther for a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth and for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houfe of our countreye, as to ſerue his prince. &amp;c. or for ſome ſpecial caſe of neceſſitie, wherby to do our ſelfe or our neighbor
<pb facs="tcp:4584:28"/> ſuche a good turne, as without perill may not be delaied (as in the harueſt &amp; ſuche othertymes to ſaue from periſhing that god hath ſente) &amp; in ſuche like caſes. For than a manne maye labour without ſcrupull of conſcience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And whan is this ſabboth violated or broken?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Whan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the ſincere preachyng &amp; diligent hearyng of the woorde of God is neglected, the holy Sacramentes not miniſtred or not receyued after the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of Chriſte, but otherwyſe or contrary to theſame, or wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Idolatry is in the ſtede of the true ſeruice of god exerciſed, the true &amp; faythfull miniſters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned and not regarded, no prouyſion made through the comon almes for the pouertie,
<pb facs="tcp:4584:29"/> but the daye miſpent in idlenes pride, wantonnes, voluptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, glottony, dronkennes, riot, bankettyng, gaming, daunſing and dalying, and ſuche lyke, and the godly exerciſes aboue rehearſed, in the meane tyme ſette a parte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And is it a great ſynne thus to violate the Sabboth?<note place="margin">Eſai. lviii.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, it is a gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous offence. For it is as much as to breake the couenaunte of God. Therfore God commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the breakyng of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente to bee punyſhed with death. Exo. xxxi.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes which we ſhould do vpon the other .vi. dayes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the workes of his owne vocacion &amp; condicion of lyfe wherunto God hath called him, to exerciſe theſame dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:4584:29"/> to the glorye of God, for the maintenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his houſeholde, and alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may haue where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to ſuccour and ayde his neybour in his neceſſitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why did god reſt vpon the ſeuenth daye?<note place="margin">Heb. ii Eſai. xlvi</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>To teache vs what ſhoulde be the ende of all our labours &amp; workes, namely euerlaſtyng reſt and quietnes in hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the fift commaundement where he ſayeth:<note place="margin">The fifthe comaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> thou ſhalt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor thy father and mother. &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>God willeth that euery man ſhould honour, eſteme, loue, and obey with all reuerence &amp; low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, theyr naturall parentes, as the lorde hymſelfe, and that we ſhould ſerue, helpe and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour them to the vttermoſte of our power in their age, ſicknes
<pb facs="tcp:4584:30"/> and in al their neceſſities, for as much as they did beare vs and tooke much trauail and ſorow, in the bringing vp of vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And are none other to bee honored, reuerenced, &amp; obeyed by this comau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our natural parentes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, all ſuche as perfourme the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; office of true parentes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs, &amp; all ſuche as haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny manier of cure or charge of vs, as our kinſfolke, teachers, tutours, ouerſeers. And ſpecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally our gouerners, rulers, and magiſtrates, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſters of the churche alſo whiche haue cure of our ſoules, our maiſter alſo &amp; myſtres, &amp; all ſuch as do vs any good through teaching, inſtructing, admoniſhi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting defendyng or maintenyng of vs, or thorowe puniſhyng &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4584:30"/> correcting vs for our fautes &amp; euil doinges, breking &amp; taming our naturall frowardnes, ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernes, proud ſtomakes, &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinatnes, intendyng nothyng but to rule, gouerne, &amp; bring vs vp to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of god, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> welth &amp; profite of our ſoules: All ſuch are we bound to obey, &amp; to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our ſelfes hartily &amp; willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto theyr inſtruccions, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, correccion. &amp;c. taking all ſuch thinges as they do vnto vs in good worthe, and withal thankfulnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But what me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the promiſe of long life an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>It ſignifieth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all ſuch as endeuor &amp; apply themſelfes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry youth vpwarde to humble &amp; ſubmit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfes obediently vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euery man that ſeketh theyr furtheraunce in all godlineſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:4584:31"/> they are woorthy to lyue long vnder good gouernaunce, and in quietnes and peace. And all ſuche as doe the contrary, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue woorthily to haue theyr lyfe ſhortened, and for their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefulnes are to bee iudged vnwoorthy to liue, except in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie &amp; calamitie. And in ſuche ſtate or caſe to lyue, is not a lyfe but a death, or at leſtwyſe a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment wurſe and more gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous then death of the bodye is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And what yf our paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, rulers, or ſuperiors would co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde vs to doe any thyng contrary to the manifeſt worde and commaundemente of God, ought we to obey them therin alſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Doubtles they haue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and authoritie ouer body, poſſeſſions, goodes, lyfe, and
<pb facs="tcp:4584:31"/> what ſo euer pertayneth vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtate of this tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſitory worlde. All whiche we ought obedient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to ſubmit vnto them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any manier grutchyng, or murmouryng But yf they goe beyond this and will take vpon them to rule alſo ouer the ſoule and conſcience of man, (whiche is the peculier regimente and poſſeſſion of God onely) and to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde vs any thyng that is expreſly againſt gods woorde, than we ought to ſaye with the Apoſtles:<note place="margin">Act. v i. Pet. iii.</note> 
                  <hi>We muſt rather obey God than man.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Yet ſ. Peter ſayeth that ſeruauntes, or ſubiectes ſhoulde obey theyr maiſters or ſuperiors though they be cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, frowarde, and extreme vnto them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>So they ought to doe in dede, ſo farre as ſuche extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie
<pb facs="tcp:4584:32"/> extendeth vnto the bodye or any thing in this mortal lyfe, and no ferther. But if ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie ſtretche vnto the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience &amp; ſoule of man, there is no obedience co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to god.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But how ſhould a man do in ſuche caſe, ſhoulde he reſiſt them with force &amp; vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>God forbid: no in no wyſe. For it is an haynous &amp; a greuous ſin, violentlie to rebell againſt our heads &amp; rulers, or to geue any maner of occaſion how light ſo euer it be, vnto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſedicion, tumulte, or inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reccion agaynſte the anoynted of the lord. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> terrible ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce of god ſhall doubtles fall vpon all ſuche, as it did v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Chore, Dathan &amp; Abiron whiche the earth did ſwallow
<pb facs="tcp:4584:32"/> vp quicke for rebelling againſt theyr rulers: but it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dutie &amp; vocacion of true chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s not to requite wrong for wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, but to be pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuffring ſide, &amp; obediently to ſuffer all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, vexacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, peines, wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs, iniuries, yea &amp; euen very death alſo (if it ſhal be the will of god) w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any maner of reſiſtence, and to refer theyr whole cauſe onlye vnto the Iudgemente of God.<note place="margin">The .vi. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Well, now what is ment by the ſixt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dmente? Thou ſhalte not kille or mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Therein is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded that we ſhoulde be readye eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye one to loue other, and not to beare any grutche, diſpleaſure, hatred, or enuy, in our harte to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward any maner of perſon, for any priuate matter, or quarell,
<pb facs="tcp:4584:33"/> nor to ſhewe any token or ſigne of malice to any man, but to be frendly, louyng, mylde, gentill, pacient both in harte, woorde, and dede, to euery bodye, what ſoeuer any man doth vnto vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But this commaundement maketh mencion onely of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, but thorowe that whiche is moſte deteſtable and horrible in this vice of murder, it would feare vs alſo from the naturall rote and head ſpryng of this ſinne, whiche is wrath, haſtines, deſier of reuengyng, and from all that whiche maye by any meanes enſue &amp; ſpryng out of this euyll roote.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Is it lawefull than for no man to reuenge and punyſhe open ſyn?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, the high powers &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, and theyr deputies,
<pb facs="tcp:4584:33"/> officers and lawfull miniſters vnder them haue authorite and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of god (whoſe minyſters they are) to reuenge with the ſweorde all iniquitie,<note place="margin">Rom. xiii</note> violence, and contempte of god, and to correcte and punyſhe all ſuche tranſgreſſions &amp; offences to the glory of God, and for the quietneſſe of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth, ſo that it bee done w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all equitie and iuſtice,<note place="margin">Sapi i. Deut. i. and .xxiiii Leui. xviiii and .xix Exo. xxiiii</note> without any carnal reſpect or parcialitie, &amp; ſo it bee after godly lawes &amp; ordynaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and not by any cruelneſſe or tyranny.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Can not the higher powers or iudges ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe their autoritie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, if they puniſhe any man that is gyltleſſe &amp; innocent, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawefully, of any malice, enuye, hatred, beyng moued through
<pb facs="tcp:4584:34"/> couetouſneſſe, or ſome pryuie grudge, or yf they procure any mans death that is innocente, or conſent vnto it, &amp; do not reſiſt all violence, and iniurye, or doe not ſaue all perſones from all mutual harmes or oppreſſions in euery behalf to the vttermoſt of theyr powers, than they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende againſte this commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demente.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is mente by the ſeuenth commaundemente whiche forbiddeth aduoutry?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Therby is commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vnto euery man to kepe himſelf pure and clene from alll maner of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſtnes, filthines and volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſnes, and from all maner of prouocacions, or examples, through worde or geſture, that myght intice any perſon eyther young or old to any vnlawfull,
<pb facs="tcp:4584:34"/> or inordinate luſtes. Likewyſe from all maner of exceſſe in ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, drinkyng, or apparell, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all maner of laſciuiouſe &amp; wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton geſtures, filthy or baudye rimes or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municacion, wherby any man may take occaſion of offence or euill, for Gods wyll is that we ſhould be pure and holy both in body, ſoule, &amp; ſpirit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe we are the temples of God, &amp; redemed,<note place="margin">Leui. xix. i. Theſ. v.</note> waſhed and ſanctified with the moſte pure, deare and precious bloud of Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But what thynkeſt thou of the lawfull vſe of matrimony?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Forſouth the lyfe &amp; company of man and wife in matrimony after the ordinaunce of God, is eſtemed of the holy ghoſte ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and he prayſeth it as
<pb facs="tcp:4584:35"/> his ordinaunce, and the veray ryght and onely meane and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medye to lyue a perfite chaſte life. And therfore it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, vnto all men of what ſtate and condicion ſoeuer they be, except they haue a ſpeciall gift, or that they be vnapt of nature therunto.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe to the .viii. commaundement.<note place="margin">The .viii commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</note> Thou ſhalt not ſteale: what is bidden or forbidden in this commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Not onely to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare ſtealyng, but alſo that I ſhould not hindre or hurte any man in his ryches or worldely goodes, through any ſubtiltie, guile, craft, deceipt, pillage, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, extorcion, priuye or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, or through any maner of vnrighteouſnes or wrongfull meanes whatſoeuer it be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:4584:35"/>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Whan kepeſt thou this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundemente?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Whan I ſubmit and offer vppe my ſelfe vtterly to God our heauenly father through our ſauior Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, that he may morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie in me, all maner of care and ſorow after worldly goodes: lykewyſe all couetouſnes, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of priuate lucre, and idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and that he may teache me to put my truſt in hym, and to be helpfull, beneficiall and piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full towarde my neighbor, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouryng truely and diligently in my vocacion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I maye haue alſo wherwith to help others.<note place="margin">The ninth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is ment by the nynth commaundement? Thou ſhalt not beare any falſe witnes. &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>That euery manne ſhould help to defende, mainteine, and
<pb facs="tcp:4584:36"/> further his neyghbours good name, fame, &amp; honeſtie, as his owne. And that no man ſhoulde lye, diſſemble, flatter towarde his neighbor, or to bear or take any maner of falſe recorde or witneſſe againſt him, or to geue ſentence and iudgemente vpon any manne falſely and vniuſtly. And here is alſo forbidden all maner of reuilyng, ſlaunderyng or backe bityng of any man, all maner of falſe iudgement, wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng, wreſtyng, &amp; concealyng of the trueth for any pryuate affeccion of enuy, malice, fauor or lucre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>whan kepeſt thou this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>whan I loue and confeſſe the trueth in all my lyfe, woordes and dedes without any falſehede or diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulacion, interpreting all wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:4584:36"/> &amp; reportes of my neighbor, as charitie requireth, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt, coueryng and excuſing as ferre as I can with honeſtie, all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that ſhould hurt my neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, whiche myght redounde vnto his ſlaundre, ſhame, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion or diſhonor.<note place="margin">The tenth commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demente.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is commaunded in the tenth &amp; laſt commaundemente? Thou ſhalt not luſt after thy neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors houſe. &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>That I ſhould neuer haue any vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full luſt, any wicked thought, deſyre or affeccion to any thyng contrary to the wil of God, but be as pure and wholly in heart, mynde, wiſhe and will, euen as Adam was before his fall, and as heauenly as the celeſtiall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Howe came any manne euer attayne vnto
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4584:37"/> my very enemies, without any reſpect of perſones at all. And all they whoſoeuer haue nede of my helpe, whether they dwell nygh vnto me or farre from me. For all theſe am I bounde to helpe and ſuccour (ſo farre as I can) by the commaundement of god. And what I cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme for lacke of habilitie, there may I wiſhe in my harte, and beare a good minde and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feccion toward all men, &amp; ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally toward myne owne houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, kinred, and ſuche as be of the houſeholde of fayth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What promiſes of rewarde or thretnynges of puniſhmente are geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the kepers or tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſers of theſe commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Euen thoſe aboue rehearſed in the .ii. commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
<pb facs="tcp:4584:37"/> 
                  <hi>J am the lorde thy God, a ſtrong and gelous God. &amp;c.</hi> by the whiche woordes he declareth vnto vs, his euerlaſtyng and immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble iuſtice, and agayne he ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth vs howe highly he eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth this his commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement, that all mankynde bothe ſmall and great, myght learne to loue feare, and humbly to obey hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Howe is god a gelous god?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>For as muche as he hath ſpouſed and maried our ſoules vnto hymſelfe,<note place="margin">Oſee. ii.</note> in euerlaſtyng loue and in the higheſt trueth and vnfaynednes, therfore he neyther can nor wyll ſuffre vs to fixe or hang our loue vpon any creature,<note place="margin">Iohn. iii.</note> but only to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried vnto hym, and to loue hym as our onely ſpouſe with our hole hart and affeccion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:4584:38"/>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Whan doeth God punyſhe the children for their parentes wickednes ſake?<note place="margin">Exo. xx Eze. xviii</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Whan the children are lyke vnto theyr pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes in wickedneſſe, and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe their parentes wicked co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And whan doeth God ſhewe mercye vnto the children for their pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſake?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eze. xviii xxxiii.</note>Whan the chyldren are ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and folowe theyr pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes properties in vertue, &amp; in the feare of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Is ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> able to kepe and fulfill the law and .x. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements of god, and ſo to attayne vnto euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng ſaluacion, of his owne naturall power and ſtrength?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>No, for than ſhould the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God, haue deſcended from heauen in vayne, whiche came downe for none other purpoſe,
<pb facs="tcp:4584:38"/> but to fulfill that for vs, which no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> els was able for weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and infirmitie, to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why hath not man free libertie to kepe hymſelfe from ſyn?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>In the firſt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acion of man before his fall, he was ſo created, &amp; had ſuche libertie. But thorow the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of Adam, we were all depriued therof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And why dyd God than geue vs ſuche commaundementes, knowing before that we wer not able to fulfill and accompliſhe them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>There are two ſpecial cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes why god gaue the lawe of the .x. commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes. Fyrſt that we myght therby learne to knowe, both that perfeccion wherein man was fyrſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp; alſo the feblenes, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="tcp:4584:39"/> and corrupcion of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, beeyng otherwyſe inclined and affect, than the lawe of god requireth. Secondarily that it myght bee our ſcholemaiſter and guide vnto the onely ſauior and mercy ſtole Chriſte, whiche is the ende of the lawe. For ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng we perceyue by the lawe that we are miſerable ſynners, and not able to perfourme that whiche the lawe requireth, we muſt nedes flee vnto Chriſt for helpe and comforte, ſtaying our ſelues vpon hym only thorowe a true and a perfecte fayth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Well, God geue vs all ſuche a fayth. Nowe what is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde ſpeciall poynte or article of the chriſten religion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The articles of the holy Chriſtian faythe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Declare me thoſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles
<pb facs="tcp:4584:39"/> of the fayth, &amp; firſt what faythe is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Faythe is a ſure truſt and a ſtedfaſte confidence in the very true, eternall, liuing god, wherthorowe our hartes are thorowly perſwaded that he wyll bee mercyfull vnto vs, thorowe the death and paſſion of his onely begotten ſonne our lorde Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto ſerueth this fayth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>It ſerueth &amp; profiteth vs for this pourpoſe, to teache vs what we muſt hope and loke for to receyue of God, whereby we may learne to knowe what god is: And it teacheth vs alſo how we may performe all that God requireth of vs in the .x. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundementes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it teache vs of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>To beleue all thinges that are wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb facs="tcp:4584:40"/> in holy ſcripture of him, the ſumme and effecte whereof is conteyned in the articles of the common crede: <hi>J beleue in God. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>How may thoſe articles be briefly deuided?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>They maye be deuided into .iii. chief &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall articles: The firſt of god the father our creator: The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of god the ſonne our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demer: The thirde of god the holy goſt our ſanctifier, which hathe ſanctified and brought vs to the knowlege of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and of the ſonne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Me thinke by this diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſte .iii. gods: god the father, god the ſonne, and god the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>No, the whole ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teacheth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is but one god, as in the .vi. of <hi>Deut.</hi> The lord our god, is one only god.
<pb facs="tcp:4584:40"/> There is but one God and one father of all. &amp;c.<note place="margin">Ephe. iiii</note>
               </p>
               <p>Item. i. Timo. ii. There is one God &amp; one mediator. &amp;c. But in theſame one Godhead are three ſondry perſons of like ſubſtance accordyng vnto the three ſondry workes whiche are knowen of God, namely the creacion, the redemcion, &amp; the ſanctificacion.</p>
               <p>Wherof the fyrſte is aſcribed vnto the father, the ſeconde to the ſonne, the thirde to the holye goſt. And for this cauſe we ſaie and beleue that there are three perſons, and but one God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Whiche are the woordes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt chiefe &amp; principal article.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>I beleue in god the father. &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is it to beleue in god?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>It is to knowe god as he is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>God is
<pb facs="tcp:4584:41"/> the euerlaſtyng and endeleſſe welſpryng of all goodneſſe,<note place="margin">Iac. i. Roma. iii</note> by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e we may ſeke whatſoeuer we lacke, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e we may ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne and complayne in what ſorow, vexacion and nede ſoeuer we be, and we ſhall be ſure to finde comforte, helpe, ſuccour and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence at him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why doeth the ſcripture call God a father?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>To confyrme and ſtabliſhe our fayth, &amp; alſo to comfort the weake and feble heartes of all faythfull beleuers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What comfort is it vnto the to beleue that God is an almyghtye fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>It is a ſingular co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort vnto me to beleue that the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, the father of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte wyll alſo be my father, and take no leſſe, but a thouſande tymes more
<pb facs="tcp:4584:41"/> care, charge, and ſorow, for me a miſerable worme, than anye naturall father can do for his child: and wyll repute and take me for a chyld and heyre of his kyngdome, &amp; euerlaſtyng lyfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Is God ſuche a father vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all men without excepcion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>No, althoughe he be the lorde, creator, and ſuſteiner of all, yet he is onely the father of the faithful which know, feare and loue, his onelye begotten ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, and put their whole truſt in him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What comforte is it vnto the to beleue that God is almightie, and creator of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and yearth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Throughe beleuyng of that I am aſſured that I maye boldly and ſafelye truſt and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitte my ſelfe vnto him, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no creature can hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:4584:42"/> or let: whiche, as he of his fatherly goodnes wyll help vs, ſo can he through his almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie power, geue to vs his heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and ayde vs in euery eaſe wherin and wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoeuer he will. Wherfore vnder his proteccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we may be of good comforte &amp; without feare of any maner of creature. For all creatures muſt ſerue vs for our wealth &amp; profite.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>If God be ſuche an almightie father, why doeth he ſuffre his chyldren ſometime to be ſo grieuouſly, afflicted and vexed, &amp; doeth not helpe them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>He ſuffereth it, not as though he would not or coulde not helpe them, but becauſe it is for the glorye of his name. &amp; for the ſufferers ſoule helth that it ſhould ſo be.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4584:42"/>
               <p>And although it ſemeth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the affeccion and deſyre of the fleſhe, yet the ſpirite of fayth feleth continually the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ayde of god, in ſuche afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Is it ſufficiente for vs thus to beleue of God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father as is nowe reherſed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>It is ſufficiente ynoughe, ſo that we learne thereby to putte all our hope and confidence of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting lyfe and ſaluacion in hym only as the head &amp; welſpring of all goodnes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mittyng our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues vnto his almyghtie pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and fatherly louyng good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Which declareth hymſelfe through his vnſpeakable wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the creacion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world after ſuche ſorte, that no manne can bee excuſed whiche dooeth not put his truſt in hym, &amp; euer
<pb facs="tcp:4584:43"/> more adore, worſhip &amp; glorifie him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>well, what foloweth next?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The ſecond principall article of God the ſonne oure ſauior Chriſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>what are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of this article?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>J beleue in Jeſus Chriſt. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is al that to ſaye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>It is thus muche to ſaye: I put al my truſt &amp; confidence of euerlaſtyng lyfe &amp; ſaluacion in Chriſte Ieſus the ſonne of God, whiche is not onelye a mightie &amp; puiſſaunt lorde ouer ſynne, death and hel, (all which he hath vtterly depriued of all theyr power and mighte, that they can neuer ouercome more) but alſo he is ſuche a lorde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs as hath boughte and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demed vs from the bondage of ſynne, and deliuered vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4584:43"/> Sathans iuriſdiccion, &amp; hath taken ſuche charge of vs, that he wyll from hencefoorth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually defende and preſerue vs, as any lorde will do his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall people that are ſworne &amp; ſubiecte vnto him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why do we call him Ieſus?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe he is an healper and ſauiour, whiche ſaueth and helpeth the children of god from ſynne and from all kynde of euill.<note place="margin">Math. i. and ix Luke. ii</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why do we call hym Chriſte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe he is the annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted king of God, which gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the children of God vnto euerlaſtyng lyfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Wherin conſiſteth his gouernaunce?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>In obteynyng vs remiſſion of our ſynnes, and in geuyng his ſpirite.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why do we ſay, <hi>his onely ſonne?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>For a differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene
<pb facs="tcp:4584:44"/> him and vs. For he was borne very god, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his beautie and glory, out of the very nature &amp; godly ſubſtaunce of the father, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all ſynne. But we are the children of god through adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and grace, whiche els by nature muſte haue remayned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children of wrathe and of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſayeſt thou,<note place="margin">Eſai ix Math. xii. Collo i. i. Cor. vi.</note> 
                  <hi>our Lorde?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe he onely hath broken the yoke of Sathan, and delyuered vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his tyranny, redemyng vs with the precious price of his bloud. Wherfore we are not our owne but his, and we ought to ſerue him onely, and to lyue after his wyll and not after our owne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What foloweth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whiche was conceyued by the holy goſt, borne out
<pb facs="tcp:4584:44"/> of the virgin Mary.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leueſt thou by this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>That our ſauiour Chriſte for our wealth is become very manne, but without all maner of ſin.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Whereby gathereſt thou that he is without all maner of ſin?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>By that that he was not conceiued by any manne, but by the holy ghoſt, and borne of the pure virgin Mary.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What profit or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte haſt thou by this belefe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>This comfort haue I therby, that I beleue that he thorowe his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and heuenly concepcion, hath ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctified our vnclene and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concepcion, and that he wyll take awaye the vncleaneſſe of my byrth and nature, and wyll make me partaker of his bliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed byrth, and of the holyneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:4584:45"/> of his nature.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why, is thy nature vncleane and vnholy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, for as muche as we all are conceyued &amp; borne in ſinne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>what other profite is it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs that the ſonne of god toke mannes nature vpon hym, and became man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>We are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red alſo thereby, that he is our brother, and that he and we are partakers of one fleſhe and bloud. And for as muche as he would ouercome ſathan in our fleſhe, we are ſure that his vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie is ours, and that we are admitted and receiued vnto the euerlaſtyng participacion of all his heauenly goodes &amp; richeſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What hath the ſonne of God Ieſus Chriſt doen for our ſake?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>He ſuffred vnder Ponce
<pb facs="tcp:4584:45"/> Pilate, was crucifyed, dyed, and was buried, &amp; deſcended vnto hel.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>what beleueſt thou in this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Hereby I beleue that Chriſt dyd ſuffre for vs the moſte vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laynous and byttereſt death, to reconcile vs, thorow the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacion of his owne bodye vnto god the father, and to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our ſynnes, and ſo to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer vs from the deuill, death, ſinne, and hell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>why was it the moſte vyllaynous death?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe he was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto death, as a blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſe, and a ſedicious perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the wycked vyllayne and murtherer Barrabas, quit and deliuered.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:4584:46"/>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why was it the moſte byt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt death?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe he was mocked, ſcourged, crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with pryckyng thornes, &amp; nailed vnto the croſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſayeſt thou, <hi>Died, was buried, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended to hell?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe he dyed verely, and his body was layed in the graue, &amp; his ſoule wente vnto the ſoules that wer before departed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What, went he in to the paynes of the damned ſoules?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>No, but vnto the holy ſoules whiche did reſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the time of Adam and Noe, in the boſome of Abraham, way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng for Chriſtes ioyfull cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And why did he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcende vnto them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>In token that the frute, vertue, &amp; effecte of his paſſion dyd not apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne only vnto them that were
<pb facs="tcp:4584:46"/> than alyue, but alſo vnto them that were dead before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>what mayeſt thou learne by all this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Forſoth .iiii. ſpeciall leſſons.</p>
               <p>Fyrſte I maye well conſyder therby, the great heauynes of my ſinne, whiche the Lorde dyd rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſome with ſo paynfull ſmart and tormente.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is the ſeconde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Secondarilye I fynde alſo a ſinguler comforte herein, whiche is this, that the Lorde hath ſatiſfied and taken awaye all my ſynnes, together with the payne whiche I had well deſerued to haue ſuffered for them, thorough his owne death &amp; bitter paſſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And what is the thirde?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I maye learne hereby paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entlye to ſuffer whatſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe the Lorde to lay vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:4584:47"/> me, and to beare my croſſe mekelye after hym euen vnto death, ſeyng he thorowe his Croſſe and paſſion hath ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed all manner of affliccions, and made them ſwete, pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and fruitefull for vs. And we maye be aſſured that if we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with hym, we ſhall alſo lyue and reygne with him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Now what is the fowerth and laſte of all?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Forſothe that is this, that I may learne hereby, the hyghe and ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable loue of God, towarde mankynde, whiche dydde not ſpare his onelye dere beloued ſoonne, but gaue hym vnto ſuche a cruell and villaynous deathe for vs vnwoorthy, my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyrable, fylthye and wretched ſinners.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What beleueſte
<pb facs="tcp:4584:47"/> thou more of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>That on the thirde daye he aroſe vp agayne from the dead, aſcended into the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, ſetteth at the ryghthande of God, the father almyghtye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is all this to ſaye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Thus muche: I beleue and confeſſe that Ieſus Chriſte the ſonne of God, beeyng without ſpotte or ſynne, coulde not bee kept, or holden with the bandes of death whiche came into the worlde, by reaſon of ſinne. And therfore thorough his godlye power, he vanquyſſhed bothe deathe and helle, and vpon the thyrde daye he aroſe agayn, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearyng vnto his diſciples in a gloryfyed and an immortall bodye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:4584:48"/>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What doeth the reſureccion of Chriſte profite vs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>For ſothe verye muche, for thereby are we aſſured that death, hell, and the deuil are ouercome, and that ſinne is taken awaye, and euerlaſtyng righteouſneſſe ſette in the place, and purchaſed of the father for vs, yf ſo be that we beleue in hym. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more it is a ſure pledge vnto vs, that our bodies ſhall alſo haue free paſſage into the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng glorye, without any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terupcion of deuil, death or hell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What meaneſt thou by this, where thou ſayeſt that Chriſte ſitteth at the righthand of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>It is a comon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſpeakyng vſed among men, whereby is ſygnifyed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hathe receyued euen after his
<pb facs="tcp:4584:48"/> mans nature, a power &amp; honor aboue all Angels &amp; creatures wherin he ruleth with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father in euerlaſtyng glorye as they do aboute kynges and prynces which ſit at theyr ryghthandes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Wherunto exerciſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord this his high &amp; godly power &amp; dominion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>He exerciſeth it in the gouernaunce of all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in heauen and vpon yearth, continually preſence therby vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all faythfull here vpon yerth, to deliuer, preſerue and defende them from all euyll, perill and daunger, and to purchaſe them of the father al that is good and neceſſarye for them praying for them continually as a true and a mercifull prieſte, patrone, and aduocate, vntyll ſuche tyme as they bee alſo exalted and taken
<pb facs="tcp:4584:49"/> vppe lyke vnto hym and with him in heauen vnto euerlaſtyng honor and glory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What doeth it helpe or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite vs to beleue that Chriſte is aſcended into heauen, and that he ſitteth at the ryght hande of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Fyrſte we are aſſured therby that the waye, dore, and entreaunce into heauen, which was before locked vnto all men by reaſon of our ſynne, is nowe opened. Secondarily, it is a ſyngular comforte vnto vs to confirme vs in pacience in all maner of aduerſitie, foraſmuch as we are ſure (by this faythe) that we haue a myghtie and a louyng protector, aduocate and ſpechemanne, with the father in heauen. Thyrdly this faythe reioyſeth and lifteth vppe our
<pb facs="tcp:4584:49"/> heartes from all yearthly, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie, viſible, and carnall thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, vnto heauenly, eternall, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible, and ſpirituall thynges, &amp; putteth vs in remembraunce to lift vppe our heartes from this yearthly and ſynfull lyfe, and to ſerue our God with heauenly &amp; ſpirituall ſeruice, and not onely with yearthly and bodilye cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Beleueſt thou any thyng els of our ſauior Ieſus?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yea forſouth, that he ſhall come from thence to iudge the quicke and the dead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What confeſſeſt thou by this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Forſouth, that my lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt ſhall come againe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen with his verye bodye, &amp; ſhall appeare before all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world viſiblye in the glorye of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſhall iudge all menne
<pb facs="tcp:4584:50"/> both ſuch as ſhall than liue and alſo thoſe whiche were before dead, to the euerlaſtyng com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte and felicitie of all faythfull whiche haue honored hym, and taken him for theyr brother, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate, patrone and defender: And agayne to the vtter confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and condemnacion of all vnfaythfull, whiche would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beleue his worde, nor ſuffer hym to rule nor to haue domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ouer them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But whan ſhall this iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t once come?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The daye and houre is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen vnto all men, wherfore no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to buſy or trouble hymſelfe muche aboute it, but euery one of vs ought continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to loke diligent aboute vs, that we do &amp; fulfyll thoſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whiche pertayne vnto our
<pb facs="tcp:4584:50"/> vocacion committed vnto vs of the lorde, that that tyme and daie come not vpon vs ſodenly, vnwares and out of ſeaſon.</p>
               <p>For the ignorance of the daye and tyme, ought to put vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually in remembraunce that we neuer lyue ſecurely &amp; reche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſelye,<note place="margin">Mat. xxiiii and .xxv Luke. xii</note> but continually wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng in the feare of God, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng alwayes prepared with the loynes of our mynde redye gyrded vp,<note place="margin">i. Peter. i. Ti. iii</note> and wayting for the Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, ſhewing our ſelues good, willyng, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente, and redye vnto all good workes wherby we maye helpe and further our neyghbor by any meanes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Do our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes than meryte any thyng of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Our workes merite nothyng of God, for any wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynes
<pb facs="tcp:4584:51"/> in themſelues, but yet God whiche of his mercy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them in and by vs, wyll al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of his mercy highly rewarde them in vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Now what foloweth next?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The thirde principall article of the holy ghoſt our ſanctifier</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What are the woordes of this article?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>J beleue in the holy goſt. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is that to ſay?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Forſouth, thus muche: I beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is an holy ghoſte whiche procedeth from the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the ſonne, with whom he is one very liuyng God, the thirde perſone in the godhead, which worketh ſo in vs that we ſhalbe partakers of the ſaluaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is purchaſed by Chriſt. Through whoſe power &amp; ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion onely, all holy men haue
<pb facs="tcp:4584:51"/> ſpoken, and without hym canne no man ſpeake or doe any thyng that is good and godly. For we haue nothyng in vs but very darkeneſſe, ignoraunce and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>what is the proper office of the holy ghoſte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>It is to ſanctifie all thoſe whiche are in the bonde &amp; coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nante of God through Chriſte, vnto the holye temples of the Lorde, that they hereafter may contende and begynne their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age vnto the euerlaſtyng lyfe, in theyr mortall body: and alſo that they may euen here in this lyfe, haue theyr God dwellyng in them. And agayne it is his office to lyghten theyr heartes with the knowlege of the father and the ſonne, to leade theim in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all trueth, to comfort them in
<pb facs="tcp:4584:52"/> al maner of temtacion, neceſſitie and aduerſitie, to prepare vs vnto a newe life, to ſtrengthen vs vnto all goodneſſe. And ſo to renewe all chriſten mennes heartes that they may be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and made newe men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But ſeyng there are many and diuers ſpirites, how may a man diſcerne and knowe the holy ſpirite, from the worldly, deueliſhe, euil and wicked ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>By the fruites &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties aboue reherſed, but ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by the holy ſcripture.</p>
               <p>For ſeyng it is certayne that ſcripture was inſpired by the holy gooſte, all maner of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that is not conſonaunte and agreable vnto it, is of an other and not of the holye ſpirite. For the holy ſpirite is
<pb facs="tcp:4584:52"/> neuer contrarye to hym ſelfe, nor neuer bryngeth in any ſtraunge doctrine in religion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What followeth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue an holy chriſten churche, the communion of ſaintes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>what is that to ſaye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>That is: I beleue and confeſſe one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany and congregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full chriſtians vpon erth from the tyme of Adam vntyll thys daye, and vntyll the ende of the worlde: whiche is ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed and incorporate into one body vnder one head, thorowe the holy goſte. And they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and agree together in oure ſauiour Chriſte, as the verye membres of one bodye, in all thynges pertayning vnto edy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying in faythe, and in all God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But howe may this
<pb facs="tcp:4584:53"/> congregacion be gathered, and ſuche edifying in faythe and all godlyneſſe perfourmed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Thorowe the worde of pure doctryne and exhortacion. And thorowe the ryghte vſe of the holy ſacramentes: And thorow other ordynaunces of diſcipline in the church, wherby the chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian congregacyon is kepte in order, after the worde of God, and ſundered from all maner of of ſtrange ſectes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why calleſt thou the churche holy and chriſten?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>For the cauſes aboue reherſed: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the holy ghoſte hathe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarlye gathered and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied it in a godlye and an holye exerciſe and lyfe,<note place="margin">i. Tho. vi</note> in body and ſowle: and alſo becauſe Chriſte hathe ſanctified it thorowe his
<pb facs="tcp:4584:53"/> precious bloud.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt thou it, the communion of ſainctes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe all they which do truly beleue in Chriſt, and are ſo ſanctified thorow his bloud (which are the very right ſainctes) wherſoeuer they bee ſcattered in the whole worlde,<note place="margin">i. Tho. xii</note> they are one bodye, one temple, vnder one head Ieſus Chriſte, with whome and with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they haue felowſhippe:<note place="margin">i. Iohn. i</note> and thorowe the holye ghoſte they are ioyned and knitte together in one God, one fayth,<note place="margin">i. cho. vi.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Ephe. iiii</note> one bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme one loue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And haue they no maner of felowſhyp with the wicked and vnfaythfull?<note place="margin">ii. cho. vi. i. cho. v</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>None at all, ſo nere as they canne knowe and diſcerne them, leſte they myght ſeme to conſente vnto
<pb facs="tcp:4584:54"/> theyr vngodlyneſſe, or perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture myght bee infecte tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe theyr wicked exaumple:<note place="margin">ii. theſ. iii</note> For the holy ghoſte commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all ſuche to bee auoyded, except they will ſuffer themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to bee admonyſhed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted,<note place="margin">ii. Ch. vii ii. theſ. iii.</note> and wyll earneſtlye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente, lamente theyr ſynnes, and amende.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth nexte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What beleueſt thou herein?<note place="margin">Eſai. xxxiii Iere. xxxi and .xxxiii Mat. xviii</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Here I confeſſe and beleue that in the holy chriſten churche, and no where els, I and all faythfull beleuers haue daylye forgeueneſſe of all our ſynnes (ſo that we hartylye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente and be ſory for them) and that the Lorde wyll neuer enter into Iudgemente with vs, nor neuer recken oure ſynnes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:4584:54"/> vs vnto dampnacion, nor neuer puniſhe vs for them with ſuche payne as they haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.<note place="margin">i. Cho. v</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>So heare I well that the chriſtians haue ſtill ſynne.</p>
               <p>But howe agreeth with this the former article, of the holy communion of ſainctes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>They are both trewe. For the churche of Chriſte thorow per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte fayth in hir brydegrome &amp; head Chriſte, is pure and holy.<note place="margin">Ephe. i. v</note> For as muche as there canne be no ſynne nor vnpureneſſe in Chriſt, but of hir ſelfe, ſhe is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſed with diuerſe infirmities and ſynnes, whiche ſhe daylye feleth, confeſſeth, and lamenteth with an heuy &amp; ſorowfull hart: And ſeketh for helpe and grace at Chriſte, and ſo reneweth hir ſelfe dayly thorow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſt,
<pb facs="tcp:4584:55"/> and laboreth contynually in mortifying the reſidewe of the olde man that ſtyll remayneth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But howe may we obteyne this dayly remiſſion of ſynnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eſai. xlv.</note>Not thorow any workes of our owne, nor yet thorowe the merites,<note place="margin">Ti. iii</note> workes or deſertes of any ſaincte that is dead, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thorowe the mere grace and mercy of God,<note place="margin">Ephe. ii.</note> vndeſerued of vs, &amp; thorowe the free rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cion of our ſauior Ieſus Chriſte, whiche hathe purchaſed and bought vs this pardone &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geueneſſe, with his precious bloud.<note place="margin">Eſai. liii.</note> For his innocent death is the ranſom of our tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſions and iniquities. As the goſpell teſtifieth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>For as muche as thou haſt made mencion of the ghoſpell, tell me, what is that
<pb facs="tcp:4584:55"/> ghoſpel?<note place="margin">Luke. i.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>To ſpeake proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is a glad &amp; ioyfull tidynges and meſſage of the grace and loue of God towarde vs, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe his ſonne Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Vnto whome is this ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell preached and publyſhed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Vnto all menne vniuerſally,<note place="margin">Mat. xvi</note> ſauyng onely ſuche as wilfully and malyciouſlye, contemne, mocke and blaſpheme it. But it ſheweth hir vertue &amp; power ſpecially, in them that are poore in ſpirite, and are ouerladen with the burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their ſinnes,<note place="margin">Mat. xi.</note> laboryng to bee rydde quite and eaſed of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Reſurreccion of the fleſhe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What beleueſt thou herein.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>By this I confeſſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that all menne that are dead
<pb facs="tcp:4584:56"/> ſhall be raiſed vp agayne at the latter daye from death.<note place="margin">Exo. iii Eſai. xxvi. Eze. lvii. Iob. xix. Iohn .v. ii Cho. v. ii Cho. xv.</note> So that euerye bodye that is dead and rotten in the yearth, or conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with water, fyer, or by any other meanes, ſhall receyue his owne forme and proporcion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne and ſhall bee vnited and knytte again with the ſoule, and ſhall ryſe vppe agayne from the dead,<note place="margin">Mat. xxviii Iohn .xx. Exo. vi.</note> immortall and incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible: Lyke as Chriſte our head is riſen vppe with his very true body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But howe can that be poſſible?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S</speaker>
               <p>By God whiche is the woorker of it,<note place="margin">Act. xxvi. ii. cho. v. Phil. iii. Gene. ii</note> is nothyng vnpoſſible, no more than it was impoſſible for him to make and create mankynde of nought.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What, is the reſurreccion of the bodye neceſſarye? Were it not enough that the ſoule alone
<pb facs="tcp:4584:56"/> ſhould reigne eyther in glorye and honor, or els in ſhame and confuſion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>It pleaſed not God that man beyng made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hope, and created vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion of two partes, (body, &amp; ſoule) ſhould only remaine with the one parte, and enioy euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting lyfe with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one alone: but that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body alſo ſhould receyue rewarde with the ſoule: and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayn for euer, holy, immortall,<note place="margin">ii. Ch. v</note> without any maner of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion or infirmitie, decked with power and honor euen as the Angels of God, yea euen after the example of Chriſt himſelfe as he was tranſformed before his diſciples vpon the mounte Tabor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>He that coulde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue this perfitely, howe coulde
<pb facs="tcp:4584:57"/> he be afrayed of death?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Luke. xxii</note>The feare of death is of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry nature, as we may perceyue in Chriſte. And foraſmuche as death is the punyſhemente of ſinne,<note place="margin">Gene. iii</note> therfore mankynd dredeth death by reaſon of his ſynne the more. Whiche feare and drede yet the faythfull beleuers do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome,<note place="margin">Philip. i</note> foraſmuche as they knowe that it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> redieſt waye vnto euerlaſtyng felicitie, to die. And for this cauſe the faithfull are not ſo vnmeaſurablye heuy &amp; ſorowfull for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of their faythfull frendes,<note place="margin">Apoca. xiiii i. theſ. iiii.</note> as the hethen and vnfaithfull are, which haue no beliefe in the reſurreccion.</p>
               <p>Lyke as the houſebande manne taketh no thought nor ſorowe for the ſede that is caſte into the
<pb facs="tcp:4584:57"/> yearth, becauſe he hath a ſure truſt &amp; hope that it ſhall come againe with a plentifull and an excedyng recompence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Now what is the laſte ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of our chriſten faith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the euerlaſting life.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is thy belief in this?<note place="margin">Soph. iii.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Hereby I confeſſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue,<note place="margin">Iohn. v i. Cho. v i. Peter. i</note> that I with bodye &amp; ſoule vnited &amp; knitte together againe after the reſurreccion, ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioye the kyngdome of God, and liue euerlaſtynglye in the ioye &amp; felicitie of heauen with oure ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uior Chriſte the ſoonne of God,<note place="margin">i. theſ. iiii Mat. xxv.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">i. cho. xv.</note> as one of the membres of his body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>what maner of ioye ſhall this be?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>That can no toungue expreſſe,<note place="margin">Eſai. lxiiii i. cho. ii</note> nor no hearte comprehende. But it ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſte ſpeciallye herein, that the
<pb facs="tcp:4584:58"/> faythful ſhall know and behold euerlaſtynglye,<note place="margin">Ion. xix Iohn. xvii</note> euen with their corporall iyes, the euerlaſtyng light and the higheſt ioye. And beyng incorporate with God for euer, ſhall haue perpetuall participacion of all heauenlye treaſures w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him.<note place="margin">Apoca. xxi Luke. xxii Pſal. xvii i. Ch. xv</note> For as than God ſhalbe all in all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But tell me more plainlye what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of perſons ſhall enioye this euerlaſtyng life?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>All they that beleue in Chriſte. Iohn. iii.v.vi.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But how muſte a man beleue in Chriſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Forſouthe that he is the ſonne of the liuing god,<note place="margin">Iohn. vi</note> whiche was ſent from god and came into this worlde and toke mannes nature vpon him,<note place="margin">Math. xvi</note> and tooke vpon hym to dye for our ſynnes,<note place="margin">i. Iohn. iiii</note> and was crucifyed vpon the croſſe, and throughe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4584:58"/> power of his godhead, roſe vp agayn from death for our iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacion.<note place="margin">Roma. iii</note> This muſt euery man beleue in his heart, and alſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly confeſſe with his mouth. Roma. x.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But here thou makeſte no mencion of the vnfaythfull: What ſhalbe doen with them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>They,<note place="margin">Dani. xii. Ihon. v Luke. xvi Eſd. xxx Math ix</note> like as they ſhall riſe vnto euerlaſtyng ſhame, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnacion, and confuſion, euen ſo ſhall they be clere deſtitute of the bleſſedneſſe, ioye and felicitie of the faythfull. And their part, ſhall be in the euerlaſtyng fyre, and in the exterior darkeneſſe, where euerlaſtyng wooe, way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, and gnaſhing of teeth ſhal be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And is this article of euerlaſtyng lyfe, of neceſſitie to be beleued?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, mooſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarye.
<pb facs="tcp:4584:59"/> For yf this article be not beleued, than are the other alſo eyther not beleued at all, or els they are beleued in vayne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>why ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe muche profite enſueth of the belefe of this article (yf it bee truly bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.) As peace and quyetneſſe of conſcience, reioyſyng in God and in his workyng, and vpon that, pacience and conſtancye in trouble and aduerſitie, and alſo tontempt of all tranſitory thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, whether it be goodes, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, or lyfe. For the ſcope and ende of al that is preſcribed and promyſed in the ſcripture, is euerlaſtyng lyfe vnto the glory of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But who will geue vs ſuche a fayth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Forſouth, that wyll God our heuenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe, yf we call vpon hym
<pb facs="tcp:4584:59"/> therfore thorowe inſtante &amp; ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt prayer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe God the father, ſonne, and holy ghoſte, geue vs and all men this fayth, and preſerue and ſtrengthen vs therin vnto the ende. Amen.</p>
               <p>What is the thirde chiefe pointe or article of the chriſten doctryne and religon?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The lordes prayer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Declare me theſame, and fyrſt what is praier?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Praier is an heartie inuocacion and callyng vpon God our heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father,<note place="margin">Math. v. vi Marke. x Iohn .xvi. Iaco. i</note> deſiryng of him in the name of Chriſte, all our neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, with a ſure truſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence that he wyll heare vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Foraſmuche as thou ſayeſt that prayer is an inuocacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and callyng vpon God, is than the inuocacion of ſainctes whiche are in heauen no ryght prayer?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:4584:60"/>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Math. vi</note>Our ſauior Chriſt ſpeaking of that prayer whiche he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to heare, ſayeth that we ſhould inuocate and praye vnto the father onely.</p>
               <p>Wherfore he that prayeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe: Fyrſt he maketh ſuch a praier, wherof he hath no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of God to be heard.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eſai xlv.</note>Secondarily, he committeth alſo idolatry, foraſmuche as he aſcribeth that thyng vnto dead ſainctes and creatures, whiche is due vnto God onely. As to be our God and father, to bee almyghtie, to ſerche &amp; to knowe the inward ſecretes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hearte,<note place="margin">i. Pa. xxviii Iere. xvii.</note> to be the fountayne of whom al that is good procedeth, and of whom all ſuccour, help, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte in any maner of neceſſitie is onely to be hoped and loked
<pb facs="tcp:4584:60"/> for. &amp;c. All theſe are due vnto God onely. He is onely to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ored or inuocate.<note place="margin">Eſa. lxiii Abraham knoweth vs not. &amp;c.</note> He is onely to be wurſhipped &amp; ſerued: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to aſcribe or attribute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe thynges vnto any other, than to hym only,<note place="margin">Mat. iiii</note> is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Idolatry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But nowe tell me, what is it to praye in the name of Chriſte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It is as muche as to praye for ſuche thynges as becummeth vs to axe, and hym to geue: namely for ſuche thynges as are hole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and neceſſarye for vs. Or els it is as muche as to praye after the commaundemente of Chriſte, and for his ſake.<note place="margin">i. Timo. ii</note> For the father geueth vs all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whatſoeuer he geueth vs for Chriſtes ſake.<note place="margin">Heb. ii</note> For the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che cauſe they onely can praye
<pb facs="tcp:4584:61"/> in the name of Chriſte, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue in Chriſte, &amp; are very ryght chriſtians, which will neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire or praye for any thyng that is or maye be, agaynſte the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and honor of Chriſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Doeth not God knowe wherof we haue nede, before we pray?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, he doeth. <hi>Math. vi</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And what nede we than to open our neceſſities vnto hym thorow praier?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>For gods be halfe we nede not at all. But for our owne behalfe it is neceſſary and good, that we maye know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and confeſſe that we haue nothyng of our ſelues but all of God: whiche thyng maketh vs meke &amp; humble.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>well, howe and after what maner ought we to pray?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Euen as our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſte taught his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb facs="tcp:4584:61"/> and no nother wyſe in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why no notherwyſe?<note place="margin">Roma. viii Math. vi</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe all maner of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that are not conſonante and agreable vnto that (whiche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth all neceſſarye peticions both for bodye and ſoule) they are not good nor auaylable.<note place="margin">i. Iohn. v</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What are the wordes of the prayer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our father whiche arte in heauen. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſayeſt thou father?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe I learne thereby that I am a chylde of god, and therfore ought to take my leaue of the deuyll for euer and to lyue onely after the wyll and pleaſure of God, and not after the deſire and luſt of myne owne fleſhe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>why ſaieſt thou our father?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>To put me in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brotherly loue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I owe towarde my neibour:
<pb facs="tcp:4584:62"/> For ſeeyng god hath receyued vs all together and all a lyke, (thorowe his ſoonne oure ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſte) vnto his chyldren, and choſen vs to be the heyres of all his goodes and treaſure, therfore we oughte to take and to loue one another, euen as brethren, and as the chyldren of one father, and truly to praye vnto the father eche one for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſayeſt thou? In heauen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>To remembre there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, his highe power, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye glory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>what comfort haſt thou by that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Euen this, that I maye (by reaſon of that) the more ſuerly ſet all my truſte and affiaunce in gods ayde and helpe, hauyng all my ioye and delight in heauen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>what is the effecte of all the peticions
<pb facs="tcp:4584:62"/> that folowe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The effecte of all is this, that the lorde will make vs partakers of al thinges that maye be good vnto vs, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer or preſerue vs from all that maye be euill and noyſome vnto vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And what order is kept in thoſe peticions?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Fyrſte we deſyre and praye therein for ſpirituall and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye thynges, and after, for worldely &amp; tranſitory thynges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>For what ſpirituall thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>For faythe, vertue and godlynes, and for remiſſion of oure ſinnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And for what worldly or tranſitory thynges?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>For all bodely nouriſhment and ſuſtentacion, whereby we maye be the more able to ſerue god with, in this life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>what is the fyrſte peticion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Halowed
<pb facs="tcp:4584:63"/> be thy name.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What prayeſt thou in this pecicion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>That God our heauenly father maye be perfectly knowen and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed throwe the whole worlde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M</speaker>
               <p>How maye that be done?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Thorowe the pure doctrine of the holy ghoſpell whan it is ſyncerelye preached and recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with a trewe and conſtante faith in all obedience, humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, holynes, and godlynes, to the confuſion of all ſinne, of ydolatrye, of blaſphemie, and of all vngodlineſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>what is the ſeconde peticion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Thy kingdome come.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What prayeſt thou for, in this peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>That God will ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe and deſtroye in vs the kyngdome of Sathan, of ſin, and of the worlde. And that he
<pb facs="tcp:4584:63"/> wyll gather vs to gether, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe his worde and ſpirite, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kyngdome of his ſonne (namely the chriſten churche, &amp; congregacion,) and gouerne and rule vs in the ſame, that we may ſerue him and liue after his will in one conſente, and whan the numbre of the faithfull, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe dayly encreaſe, is once full and perfecte, than that we may together inherite and enioy that euerlaſtyng kyndome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>what is the thirde peticion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thy will be doen vpon erth. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>what praieſt thou for in this peticion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>That we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſuch a luſt and a deſire vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his will in all thynges, as the holy Angels and ſaintes in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen haue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſayeſt thou in earth as it is in heauen?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:4584:64"/>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe that in heauen no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing reſiſteth the wyll of God, but in yearth the wyll of God is muche and often reſiſted.</p>
               <p>Therfore doe we praye in this peticion that God wyll hyndre and let whatſoeuer is agaynſte his moſte holye wyll, geue vs grace to forſake our owne fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wyll and deſyre, and withall humbleneſſe to obey his moſte godly wyll, ſubmittyng and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng ouer our ſelues willyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto the ſame, whatſoeuer he ſhall laye vpon vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>what is the fowerth petici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Geue vs this day our daily bread.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What prayeſt thou for, in this peticion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>That God wyll geue vs all maner of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ſuſtinaunce for this lyfe, as meate, drynke, clothyng,
<pb facs="tcp:4584:64"/> godly and vertuous magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and rulers, helth, peace, and quietnes, and all thynges what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is neceſſary for vs to liue in thys worlde, to the glorye of hys name and the profite of our neighbor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſayeſt thou, <hi>this day and dayly?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>By thoſe wordes I am put in remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that I ſhould take no thought nor be carefull for the time to come, but ſhould dayly labor (in my condicion of lyfe) and praye therwith, &amp; than nothyng doubte but that God wil geue me both that day, and all dayes as long as I lyue, whatſoeuer I ſhall nede, &amp; may be profitable and expedient for me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is the fifte peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>For geue vs our treſpaces. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What prayeſt thou for in
<pb facs="tcp:4584:65"/> this peticion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>For remiſſion and forgeuenes of ſuche ſynnes wherwith I dayly dipleaſe my heauenly father, and that God wyll not entre into iudgemente with me, but be mercyfull vnto me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And why than kepeſt thou not thy ſelfe from ſinning?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>I ought ſo to doe withall diligence and indeuor, but our naturall ignoraunce, with the weakenes &amp; infirmitie, wherein we were borne, is ſo great, that we ouerſee oure ſelues euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, and therfore are we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned to deſyre God of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuenes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why addeſt thou further, <hi>as we forgeue our treſpacers?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>For the lorde wyll not remit or forgeue vs at all, yf we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue greued, offended, or diſpleaſed vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:4584:65"/>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe our heauenly father wylleth that we ſhoulde well conſider and acknowelege our owne ſynnes, and take all maner of diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of iniury that our neighbor doeth vnto vs, pacientlye and with thankefulnes, euen as a moſte worthy deſerued puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and therfore (for our owne part) to be well content with al ſuch, through whom God doth chaſtice or puniſhe vs, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is the ſixt peticion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leade vs not into temptacion.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What praieſt thou for in this peticion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>That God our heauenly father wyll mercyfully aſſiſt me in all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of temptacions, and bryng me through, whether it bee in
<pb facs="tcp:4584:66"/> proſperitie or aduerſitie, &amp; wyll kepe and preſerue me by the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye ryght fayth, euen vnto the ende.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Howe doeth god leade men into temptacion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Whenſoeuer he permitteth the wicked ghoſtely enemy, to withdrawe vs through tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory fortune or miſfortune, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie or aduerſitie, and alſo through other goſtly aſſaultes from fayth, vertue &amp; godlines.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is the ſeuenth peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But deliuer vs from euill.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What prayeſt thou in this peticion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>That our heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father will redeme &amp; deliuer vs from the ſnares, ſubtiltie, tyranny, and power of our olde wicked enemy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Hath he than any power agaynſt thee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yea forſouth, by reaſon of
<pb facs="tcp:4584:66"/> my ſynnes wherin I am borne, god geueth him power againſt me, from the which he himſelfe alone through our Lord Ieſus Chriſte, muſt nedes deliuer me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And what meaneth that clauſe and ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wheras thou ſayeſt? <hi>For thine is the kyngdome, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and glory for euer.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>That ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence putteth vs in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce, that we ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude and ende all our prayers in lauding and prayſyng of god, and to thynke thus in our hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: O heauenly father I haue deſyred of the to the glorye of thy name, and to the wealth of all men (both in body &amp; ſoule,) high and excedyng great thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whiche are by menne im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to obteyne or atteyne.
<pb facs="tcp:4584:67"/> But thou arte a gloryous and an almyghtie puiſſaunte kyng euerlaſtyng, whiche canſte ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily procure &amp; prouyde all that is good for thy chyldren, and canſte alſo breake and auoyde all contrarye power of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, wherfore helpe and deliuer vs from all the power of hel, and reſtore vs vnto euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng lyfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But nowe howe concludeſt thou thy prayer?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>With this woorde. Amen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is that to ſaye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Forſouth, thus muche: O heauenly father, graunte of thy mercye, that all theſe thynges maye come to paſſe whiche we haue deſired of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in this prayer. And foraſmuche as thou haſte
<pb facs="tcp:4584:67"/> promiſed to heare all thoſe that call vpon the in true faith, in the name of thy beloued ſonne, we hope and truſt ſtedfaſtly that it ſhall ſo happen vnto vs.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lacke of defaute in our fayth by reaſon or our naturall infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, than ſtrengthen thou good lord, our fayth, &amp; graunte vs thy holy ſpirite, that we may praye this thyne owne prayer with a true and a perfite fayth, and that we maye ſpeake from the botome of our heartes vnto the in all our prayers, Amen, Amen, Sobeit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Almyghtie God graunte that thou and all other maye alwayes praye in ſuche a fayth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Amen.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:4584:68"/>
            <head>A declaracion of the holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Baptiſme.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe what is the fowerth principall article of the chriſten doctrine and religion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Forſouth that is the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the holy ſacramente of baptiſme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Fyrſt tel me, what are ſacramentes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>They are holy viſible acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and exterior exerciſes inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, ordeyned, and appoynted of almighty God to bee vſed in hys churche and congregacyon of hys faythful to repreſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theim after a mooſte lyuely ſorte, his heauenly gracious be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites, that they may therby be confirmed in theyr fayth, and of purpoſe to excite y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mutual loue of one towarde an other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why did Chriſte ordayne
<pb facs="tcp:4584:68"/> ſuche ſacramentes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>For .iii. ſpeciall cauſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is the firſte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The fyrſte is, that they ſhoulde be tokens and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the grace, mercy and promiſes of God towarde vs, and as the moſte ſure ſeales, wherby our participacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp and incorporacion with Chriſt, is confyrmed, conſigned and ſealed vp.</p>
               <p>And alſo that our faythe, which is otherwyſe veraye feble and weake, myght thorowe the vſe of them be exerciſed and lifte vp from all earthly thinges, vnto the conſideracion, eſtimacyon, and expectacion, of celeſtiall and heauenly thinges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Is not that the peculiar operacion and office of the holy gooſte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yes it is the very proper operacion
<pb facs="tcp:4584:69"/> of the holy goſt. For he gloryfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Chriſte, &amp; he is the eternall and effectuous worker and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutour of all the doctryne and ordinaunces of Chriſte. But yet he perfourmeth and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> worke thorowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde and vſe of the ſacramentes, yf they be truely miniſtred and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued: And it is therfore aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed vnto them, becauſe we ſhould vnderſtande and knowe that the ſacramentes are not bare, vayne, and vnprofitable tokens.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is the ſeconde cauſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The ſeconde is this: that they ſhoulde admoniſhe vs continuallye of our office and duetie as long as we lyue. For ſeyng we profeſſe by receyuyng and vſyng of the ſacramentes, that we are incorporate and
<pb facs="tcp:4584:69"/> made one bodye with Chriſte thorowe participacion of hym, we ought to knowe alſo that it is our bounde dutye to expreſſe and repreſent the very image of Chriſte in our whole lyfe and in all the exerciſes of the ſame. And yf we doe not ſo, than we contemne the ſacramentes and vſe them vnworthely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is the thyrd cauſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>That they ſhoulde be tokens of the people of god, wherby the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany and congregacion of god myght bee gathered together as it were into one bodye, and ſeparated or diuided &amp; knowen by ſuche ſeuerall tokens and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar exerciſes (whiche no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther congregacion doeth vſe,) fro all other falſe ſectes. And they ſerue alſo for this purpoſe
<pb facs="tcp:4584:70"/> that the congregacion of Chriſt may ſhewe and declare by them theyr ſeruice, reuerence and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience towarde God, and ſo maye prouoke others alſo tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe their exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple vnto the trew religion and ſeruice of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What thinkeſt thou of them whiche vſe the ſacramentes vnwoorthely and vnreuerent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>For as muche as they breke &amp; violate the couenaunte of the Lord therby, they are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed and abominable in the ſyght of God. And therfore they ſhall bee reiected and refuſed of the Lorde for euer, as periured rebellions, yf they do not turne and amend.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Who vſeth the ſacramentes vnreuerently, and vnworthily?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Forſoth he that doth not vſe them in true fayth,
<pb facs="tcp:4584:70"/> loue, and obedience towardes God: &amp; ſpecially he that vſeth them not to prouoke, ſtyrre vp, and to nouriſh, the forſaied ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. For therunto ought the vſe of all externall or outwarde ſacramentes to ſerue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But are the ſacramentes neceſſarye vnto ſaluacion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Foraſmuch as they are the ordinaunces of God, and commaunded vnto vs to be vſed in perfecte obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towarde God: therfore can we not forbeare or neglecte the vſe of them, without manifeſt perill and hinderaunce of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What perſons are to bee taken and reputed for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners and diſpiſers of the ſacramentes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Suche as vſe them not whan they maye haue them miniſtred after the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tucion
<pb facs="tcp:4584:71"/> and ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>For whoſoeuer beleueth our ſauiour Chriſte, and is a true diſciple of his, he can not choſe but to vſe all thinges with high reuerence and deuocion, what ſoeuer our ſauior Chriſte hathe ordayned to bee vſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Well, nowe lette vs come vnto bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme? what is Baptiſme?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>It is an ordinaunce &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente of oure ſauiour Ieſus Chriſte, ioyning all ſuche as ſhall enter into the cumpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and congregacion of Chriſte, to be baptiſed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, to bee ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cled or dipped with water in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of the father, of the ſonne, and of the holy goſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But in what texte of ſcripture is ſuche commaundemente grounded?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>In the laſt of Matthew, and
<pb facs="tcp:4584:71"/> Marke, in theſe wordes: Vnto me is geuen all power in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, therfore go your waye, and teache all nacions, baptiſyng them in the name of the father, and of the ſonne, and of the holy ghoſte. &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is to be noted &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out of theſe wordes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoth .iii. thinges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>what is the fyrſte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The fyrſte is this, that our ſauior Chriſte vnto whome the father hath geuen all power in heauen &amp; earth, wylleth that his holy goſpell ſhould be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vnto all men in the whole worlde, &amp; that all people ſhould be made his diſciples.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>what is the .ii. note?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The .ii is this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the holy ſacramente of baptiſme is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded of god the father, the ſonne, and the
<pb facs="tcp:4584:72"/> holy ghoſt, to be aſure teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the ineſtimable loue &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God toward vs, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the promiſes of the ghoſpell, concernyng the free remyſſion of ſynnes, the newe byrth, and euerlaſtyng lyfe purchaſed by Chriſte, are ſealed, confyrmed and made ſure vnto vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And what is the thyrde note?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The thirde is this, that thoſe that are baptiſed ought to remayne in the couenaunte of God, and to applye themſelues to learne and to kepe all that the Lorde hath commaunded, to dye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſynne, and to caſte of the olde Adam, with all his luſtes and affeccions, &amp; to put on the Lord Ieſus euery daye more than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a newe lyfe, whiche will be preſente with vs vntill the
<pb facs="tcp:4584:72"/> worldes ende, and graciouſlye ayde and helpe vs therunto.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Vnto what perſons doeth baptiſme appertayne?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Vnto all ſuche as the couenaunte of God &amp; the doctryne of the ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell preached by the Apoſtles pertayneth vnto.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Muſte infantes and young children alſo be baptiſed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yea forſouth yf it maye be done, foraſmuche as the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde perteyneth alſo vnto them, &amp; they are alſo of the flocke of God, and partakers of grace. And therfore the ſigne and ſeale of the promiſe and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenaunte (whiche is baptiſme) muſte nedes alſo perteyne vnto them. And agayne ſeeyng they are in the fauor of God, as his dearely beloued, and partakers
<pb facs="tcp:4584:73"/> of Chriſte &amp; of his merites (as they muſt nedes be yf the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of god be the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as Chriſte ſayth) than baptiſme whiche is the ſeale of all this, muſte alſo nedes perteyne vnto them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But howe can they be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed ſeyng thei haue no faythe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Foraſmuche as they haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fauor of God through Chriſte, whatſoeuer is required in them, that haue thei alſo ſufficientlye in and through Chriſte, whiche hath taken theyr weakenes v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon himſelfe, &amp; is become their ſatiſfaccion as he is to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And his fayth and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is (of grace) imputed vnto them, and throughe his ſpirite they are ſanctified to bee the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of God, whoſe heade and ſauior is Chriſte, and they
<pb facs="tcp:4584:73"/> membres of his body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Than may they be baptiſed with a good conſcience?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yea no doubt. For ſeyng they are reputed as faythfull in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyghte and iudgement of god thorowe Chriſte, they ought as faythfull to bee baptiſed, that thorowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſtracion of the churche they may haue a ſure token &amp; witnes that they are the heyres of the bleſſyng promiſed vnto the ſede of the faythfull, the membres of our ſauior Chriſte, &amp; cleane pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and waſhed from all theyr ſynne in his bloude.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>From what ſynne nedeth a chylde that is newe borne (whiche hath wrought neither good nor euil) to be purged or waſhed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>From original ſinne, whiche is the verye roote of all other
<pb facs="tcp:4584:74"/> ſynne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is originall ſinne?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>It is the poiſon, infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion or corrupcion, of nature wherein we are conceyued: Whiche alwayes reſiſteth, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belleth and luſteth againſte the wyll of God, and is euer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined and redye vnto all euill &amp; wickednes, and hath a luſte and delite therin. From the whiche we can none otherwyſe be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered or pourged, but alonlye throughe the power of God in our ſauior Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But how are we pourged from this ſinne through baptiſme?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>In as muche as in baptiſme we haue a promiſe that it is forgeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs and not imputed to damnacion vnto vs. And againe that the holy ghoſt is alſo geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſhall dayly mortifie, kyll and
<pb facs="tcp:4584:74"/> ſubdue this ſynne and wicked inclinacion in vs, begynnyng and daylye increaſyng in the ſtede therof, a newe affeccion and nature in vs, obediente vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wyll of God and deliting therin, whiche in the bleſſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurreccion ſhall bee altogether perfite.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe tell me what ought our baptiſme to worke in vs and to put vs in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Firſte we ought to bee thankefull vnto God for it, and vnto our parentes alſo for furtheryng and healpyng vs vnto it, and to receyue all doctrine and correccion of them obediently and redily.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What more?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>It ought alſo to put vs in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our ſynnes, of the grace and mercye of God, and of the
<pb facs="tcp:4584:75"/> bleſſed reſurreccion wherin we ſhall aryſe agayne vnto euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng lyfe. By the remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wherof we maye haue a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar comforte agaynſt all ſynne, agaynſt the deuyll, death, hell, &amp; damnacion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And what els?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Finally, it ought to worke in vs a perfite obedience vnto the wyll of God, to leade our liues in continuall repentaunce and amendemente, praying er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly that he wyll ſtrengthen and make more perfite in vs, through his holy woorde and ſpirite, the newe byrth whiche is already begonne in vs: and dayly to mortifie our fleſhe and to practiſe with all faythfulnes and diligence to ſerue God and to kepe his commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:4584:75"/>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe, what is the .v. ſpeciall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the chriſten doctrine or reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The holy ſupper of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is the ſupper of the Lorde?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>It is an holy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance and inſtitucion of our ſauior Chriſte, wherby chriſten people are commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to eate and drynke the bread and cuppe of the Lorde together, &amp; therby to remembre his paſſion, and to be aſſured of theyr commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with hym in his body and bloud. For it is a pledge and an aſſuraunce that the Lorde geueth them his bodye &amp; bloud to be the foode and nouriſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of theyr ſoules vnto euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng lyfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Than is it not a bare ſigne and an vnfruitfull token?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>No. For we receyue in the ſupper a ſpirituall meate
<pb facs="tcp:4584:76"/> and drinke, wherin by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes owne inſtitucion, the true com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and participacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the bodye and bloud of Chriſte is moſt liuely repreſented and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed vnto vs. And at the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtracion therof, beeyng mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred after Chriſtes inſtitucion, it is certayne that he is alwaies preſente, and worketh effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly therwith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>How ought this ſupper to be miniſtred?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>In euery poynte &amp; condicion as the Lorde himſelfe dyd mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre and ordeyne it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Where is it written how the lorde did mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtre and ordeyne it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>In the holy Euangeliſtes,<note place="margin">Mat. xxvi. Marc. xiiii Luke. xxii</note> Matthew, Marke, Luke. And in the .xi. Chapiter of the fyrſt Epiſtle to the Corinthians in theſe woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. <hi>In the ſame night that the Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:4584:76"/> Jeſus was betrayed, he tooke bread, and whan he had geuen thankes, he brake it.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What learneſt thou out of theſe wordes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Fyrſt I lerne that this ſupper ſealeth vp, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, &amp; aſſureth vnto vs, the verye true communion of the true body and bloud of Chriſt, with all the frutes and benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, whiche he dyd euer pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe and merite thorowe his body &amp; bloud.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Howe canſte thou proue that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>By the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye woordes of the inſtitucion. For whereas he commaundeth vs to eate his body and drynke his bloud, that is to ſaye, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue our nouryſhement vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyng lyfe, thorowe fayth, of his bodye and bloud, he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth immediatlye: <hi>Whiche is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vp for you, and ſhed for you.</hi> By the
<pb facs="tcp:4584:77"/> whiche woordes he ſignyfieth, ſeeyng we are partakers of his bodye and bloud, and in faythe fleſhe of his fleſhe, and bones of his bones, he our head and we his members, that we are alſo partakers of all that he did euer purchaſſe or merite thorow his paſſion and bloud ſhedyng, that is, reconciliacion with God the father, remiſſion of our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, righteouſnes and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting lyfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What lerneſt thou more out of the forſayed woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>I learne alſo that the Lorde geueth me thorowe this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, a ſure hope and comforte that I am partaker of the new teſtament, and of the couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of grace whiche he confirmed
<pb facs="tcp:4584:77"/> and ſealed with his precious bloud.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is that newe Teſtamente or couenaunte of grace?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>It is this, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghtye God, for the bitter paſſion and deathes ſake of his deare beloued ſonne, wyll freely pardon and forgeue me all my ſynnes, and take me for his childe and heyre, and at the latter daye will rayſe me vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne vnto euerlaſtyng ioye, requiryng that I ſhould beleue all this ſtedfaſtly, and loue and ſerue him obediently.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And is nothyng els to bee noted in the woordes of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitucion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, this alſo is to be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that al they which miniſter or receyue this holy ſacramente
<pb facs="tcp:4584:78"/> muſte celebrate &amp; kepe the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall or remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our ſauiour Chriſte Ieſus.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Wherin conſiſteth this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall or remembraunce?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>It co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth ſpecially herein, that we beeyng aſſembled and gathered together in his name, conſidre and ſetfoorth with all diligence and reuerence all the benefites of our Lorde Ieſus, whiche he hathe doen and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for vs, or will yet hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter do for vs: And agayne that we render moſte highe laudes and thankes vnto him for ſuche excellente benefites, geuyng vp and yeldyng our ſelues whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What maner of people are to bee admytted vnto this ſupper?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>All that are truly repentaunte and ſorye
<pb facs="tcp:4584:78"/> for their ſinnes, and yet beleue ſtedfaſtlie that god for Chriſtes ſake wyll be mercyfull vnto them, and that they are the true membres of Chriſte, liuing in the feare and true obedience of the Lord, and in perfect loue of theyr neighbour, as brethren of one kyngdome, membres of one bodye, and redemed with one bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye to confeſſe the doctrine of the holy goſpell, in the middes of all perſecucion and afflicci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to defende it euen vnto death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>what thinkeſt thou of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche will neuer receiue this holy ſupper with the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full congregacion of Chriſte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>If they abſtaine from it wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye of concempte and ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernes, that is to ſaye, yf they
<pb facs="tcp:4584:79"/> maye haue it miniſtred vnto them after the inſtitucion of the Lorde, and yet regarde it not and will not receyue it, it is an euidente token that they pertayne nothing at all vnto the body of Chriſte. For whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beleueth in the Lorde truly can not neglecte or contemne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his hollye ordinaunces, but with all reuerence vſe them, as ofte he maye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Where as ſ. Paul ſayeth: <hi>Lette euery manne proue hymſelfe, and ſo eate of that bread:</hi> What is mente therby, or whan eate we this ſupper wurthyly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Of our ſelues we can neuer be woorthy vnto it: But God of his grace and mercye, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puteth vs woorthy of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye miſteries and benefites, whanſoeuer we referre the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
<pb facs="tcp:4584:79"/> of oure ſinnes, and oure ſaluacion vnto the death and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurreccion of Chriſte, and ſeke it therat onely.</p>
               <p>Wherfore whanſoeuer I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſupper, with this faythe and belefe that Chriſte Ieſus gaue his tender bodye vnto death for me, and ſhedde his precious bloud for me, and ſo redemed me from euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng deathe: And that his fleſhe and bloude are the foode and ſuſtenaunce of my ſoule whereby I am refreſſhed and nouriſſhed vnto euerlaſtynge lyfe, ſubmitting my ſelfe, in this faythe, hartilye and fullye both bodye &amp; ſoule vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> will of god, and vtterly deteſting in word, dede, and example alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſinne, and wickednes,
<pb facs="tcp:4584:80"/> and whatſoeuer maye geue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny occaſion therunto. &amp;c. then receyue I this hollye ſupper wurthyly. For this is the true communion and participacion of Chriſtes bodye and bloud, wherby we are ſure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in vs, and we in hym. For els we coulde doe none of this at all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Me thynketh by thy anſwers, that the holy ſupper of the Lorde ſendeth and refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs all together vnto the deathe and paſſion of Chriſte, that we maye ſo &amp; by that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes enioye and haue fruicion of the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yea forſouth, for whan he ſuffred vpon the croſſe then he was made the onely &amp; euerlaſtyng ſacrifice, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente for our ſaluacion: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is nothyng remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng
<pb facs="tcp:4584:80"/> for vs more, but that we maye enioy and haue the fruici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And was not the ſupper ordeyned of God to bee a propiciatory ſacrifice, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the body of Chriſte ſhould be offered vnto God of freſhe or of newe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>No forſouth. For that were iniurious vnto his death. And the woordes doe ſounde thus, <hi>take and eate. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where he commaundeth vs not to ſacrifice or to offer his body, but onely to eate. &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And why was it ordeyned to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in two diuerſe kyndes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>That was done for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities ſake, to teache vs the more plainly that he is not only the meate wherwith our ſoules are noriſhed, but alſo the verye drynke wherwith they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed,
<pb facs="tcp:4584:81"/> that we ſhoulde ſeke no parte of our ſpirituall lyfe any where els, ſauyng at hym and in hym alone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And ought all men generally without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion to receyue both kyndes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yea for ſouth, ſo do the woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of Chriſte commaund, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, drinke ye all of this: from the whiche to derogate or my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe any thyng it were an hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous ſynne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But now, how oughteſte thou to behaue thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe after thou haſte thus recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued this holy ſupper?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>I oughte fyrſte to reioyce in the remiſſion of my ſynnes, in the lyfe of Chriſte in me, and in the bliſſed reſurreccion, whan as he ſhall lyue fully in me and in vs, &amp; be all in all. And thus to auaunce my ſelfe agaynſte
<pb facs="tcp:4584:81"/> ſynne, agaynſt the deuyll, death, and hel: And to geue God eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall thankes for all theſe his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedyng benefites.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What oughteſt thou els to doe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>I ought alſo to ſubdue, to tame, and to crucify, mine owne fleſhe and bloud, with al maner of wicked luſtes and affeccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; to liue, hereafter as a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of that body onely, whoſe head is Chriſte, and not as a membre of any other body. But vtterly to yelde and geue ouer myſelfe vnto my lorde God, to bee one breade and one bodye with all faythfull chriſtians whyche doe truely inuocate and call vpon the name of the Lorde, to lyue with them in perfite loue and charitie and wyth this bande of loue to haue my heart fixed
<pb facs="tcp:4584:82"/> and knitte vnto theirs, and thus euermore to remayne &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue.</p>
               <p>And I ought alſo to confeſſe and magnifie my Lorde Ieſus in his churche and congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion with all my woordes and dedes, awaytyng dayly to haue this lyfe changed with a better and into a better lyfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What yf we receyue the ſupper with ſuche as be vnwoorthy, doe we make our ſelues alſo vnworthy by reaſon of that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>No we doe not, if ſo be that we conſente not vnto theyr ſynnes, but haue in mynde and will yf we can know them and may come vnto them, to exhorte and admoniſhe them faythfully our ſelues, or els cauſe ſome other to doe it. For it pertayneth vnto no priuate perſon to exclude any man out
<pb facs="tcp:4584:82"/> of the churche or congregaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but onely vnto the whole churche, or vnto them that are choſen &amp; appointed of the ſame vnto that office. And theyr duetie it is to conſidre bothe in this matter and all other, what may be moſt profitable and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediente vnto edificacion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But nowe, why ſhould men receyue this ſacramente ofte, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they receyue the ſacramente of baptiſme but once?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is a ſacramente of ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce into the religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt, and betokeneth that menne are nowe dead vnto the olde lyfe, &amp; wyll from thencefoorth walke in a newe lyfe. Wherfore lyke as Chriſte died but once, &amp; that for our ſynnes, and ſhall from hence foorth dye no more, euen
<pb facs="tcp:4584:83"/> ſo ought the ſacrament of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, whiche repreſenteth the ſame, to bee receyued but once. But the holye ſupper is a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of procedyng and goyng forward in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> religion of Chriſt, and ſignifieth that the manne whiche is once incorporate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſte, and fed or ſuſteyned continually through hym, wyll euermore continue, procede and goe forwarde in a perfite chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian life. And foraſmuche as many impedimentes, lets and temptacions, doe chaunce vnto ſuche menne by the waye, which notwithſtandyng doe ſtyll hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre and thurſt after ryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And this ſupper is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable pledge or ſeale of the true lyuely foode of the ſoule, it is the heauenly bread, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:4584:83"/> whiche this hounger canne not bee ſatiſfyed nor aſſuaged. Therfore ſhoulde they receyue this ſacrament oft, becauſe they haue oft nede of ſuche comforte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe which is the ſixt ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall article of the chriſten doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The eccleſiaſticall or churche diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline or brotherly correccion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Where is any commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement therof in the ſcripture?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>In the .xviii. cha. of Matthew in theſe wordes. <hi>If thy brother ſinne againſt the, goe thy way and correct hym betwene the and hym alone. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is to be noted out of theſe woordes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Thre ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all poyntes. Fyrſte, that euery chriſten man ought to correcte &amp; admonyſhe other of hys faute pryuately and gently. And yf
<pb facs="tcp:4584:84"/> he cannot doe it hymſelfe, than to cauſe ſome other to doe it for hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What ſhoulde bee the cauſe that euery man ought to admoniſhe other? Shall not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man anſwere for himſelfe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Forſouth this is the cauſe: for aſmuche as all faythfull are incorporate vnto our ſauiour Chriſte in baptiſme, as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres of one body, and are altogether chyldren and heyres of God, and haue like parte and felowſhippe of one euerlaſtyng heritage, therfore ought eche one to ſaue and preſerue the other from hel and from euerlaſtyng damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, through godly correccion and admonicion, and ſo to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his brother vnto heauen and vnto euerlaſtyng lyfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But howe ſhoulde this bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly
<pb facs="tcp:4584:84"/> correccion and warnyng, be putte in vre and be exerciſed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>With all humbleneſſe and frendlyneſſe, and alſo with ſuch wyſedome and ſobreneſſe, that his good name bee not hynde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but that he maye perceyue that none other thing is ſought thereby ſauyng alonely hys welth and emendemente.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>How ofte ſhould he be thus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyſhed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Euen as ofte as there is any hope of his amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demente by ſuch correccion and warnyng.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>why doeth Chriſt commaund the to take one or .ii. vnto the, yf thy brother will not amende at the warning and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reccion of thee alone?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>That he ſhoulde the more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtlye bee conuinced of his faulte, and not hable to denye
<pb facs="tcp:4584:85"/> it beyng correct or admonyſhed therof by .ii. or .iii. wytneſſes (as the lorde teacheth,) onely to wynne hym therby.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is the ſeconde note out of the fore reherſed wordes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The ſeconde is the correccion of the churche.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>who ſhould execute that correccion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Forſouth ſuche as are choſen and apoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the whole congregacion to be aſſiſtente vnto the miniſter in that behalfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Towarde what maner of parſons ſhould ſuche correccion and admonicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be exercyſed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Towarde ſuche as either regard not the priuate and ſecrete warnyng, or els as offende the churche and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacion with ſome greuous and notable enormytie, that is manyfeſt and open.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Out of
<pb facs="tcp:4584:85"/> whiche woordes learneſt thou that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Out of theſe woordes where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde ſaieth, yf he heare the not, (beyng admoniſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore .ii. or .iii. witneſſes.) <hi>Than tell it vnto the whoſe congregacion. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And S. Paul wrytyng vnto Tymothe the miniſtre of the church of Epheſus confirmeth theſame, where he ſayeth: ſuche as haue ſined, correct or rebuke them openly, that other may be afrayed by theyr exaumple.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And ſhould all that offende bee put vnto open ſhame before the whole congregacion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>No, not put to open ſhame, but earneſtlye driuen and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhed vnto repentaunce. And ſuch moderacion muſt be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued therin, as maye be thought beſt and moſte conueniente to
<pb facs="tcp:4584:86"/> moue and wynne the ſynner vnto perfecte and trewe repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Is it the dutye of thoſe that are choſen and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of the congregacion to bee aſſiſtente vnto the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, onely to correcte and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyſhe ſuche as haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted open and manyfeſt cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and ſuch as would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the pryuate and brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly correccion, and none other?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>No, not this onely, but as trewe fathers and phiſicions, they ought to haue an iye and a regarde vnto all menne, and to warne and exhorte euery one, as they canne thinke it moſte ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarye for the edificacion and emendemente of euery one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Where haſt thou any ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Paul wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng
<pb facs="tcp:4584:86"/> vnto the Theſſalonians co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmeth it by his owne exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in theſe woordes. <hi>You knowe, ſayth he, that we haue exhorted and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted euery one of you, euen as a father doeth his children, and we haue teſtified that ye ſhould walke worthely as it beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth you before God whiche hathe called you vnto his kyngdom &amp; vnto his glory.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Well, what is the thyrde pointe that thou noteſt out of the fore reherſed woordes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The thirde is the byndyng and the loocyng.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What is it to bynde?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>It is as muche as to exclude a manne out of the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip or company of Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people, whereby he maye be er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtlye forced vnto a ſpecyall and an vnfeyned declaracion of true repentaunce and amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his lyfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:4584:87"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4584:87"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4584:88"/> of people ought ſo to bee bound?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>All ſuch as wyll not heare the Churche &amp; congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion reprouyng and admony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their ſoule helth, and all they alſo which haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the churche and congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion with any manifeſt, gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, and notable crimes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The lorde maketh mencion onely of ſuche as wyll not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the warnyng and correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the churche.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>But he hathe taught vs alſo thorowe the holy Apoſtle.<note place="margin">i. Co. v.</note> ſ. Paul to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude out of the felowſhip &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacion of Chriſte, all ſuche as are fallen into whoredome, and other notable vices, and to force or drieue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto ſome ſpeciall penaunce to be vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a correccion vntil thei declare
<pb facs="tcp:4584:88"/> with manifeſt frutes of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, an erneſt ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may edifie &amp; content the churche &amp; congregacion againe which they had before thorowe theyr greuouſe ſinnes offended.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe what is it to loocen?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>It is as much as to pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce forgeuenes of ſinnes, vnto ſuch as haue declared their repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; amendment with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect erneſtnes, and to admit and receyue the ſame perſons agayn vnto the felowſhyp and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the churche or congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion, and alſo of the holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And muſt none be looced from theyr ſinnes but ſuche as declare earneſtelye theyr repentaunce and ſorowe for their ſinnes with plaine and euidente amendemente of theyr
<pb facs="tcp:4584:89"/> lyfe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>No, none els: For the Lorde commaundeth remiſſion and forgeueneſſe of ſinnes, to be pronounced and declared one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto ſuche as repente and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayle theyr ſynnes, and deſyre and purpoſe truely to emende themſelues. For the eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call diſciplyne ordeyned of God for the order and edifiyng of his churche, ought to bee exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted and practiſed trulye and earneſtly, and not fayntlye or feynedlye for a ſhyne and a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour onely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>In whiche wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des is that commaunded of the Lorde?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>In theſe woordes, where he ſayeth: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erely I ſaye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you: whatſoeuer you ſhall bynde vpon yearth, that ſame ſhalbe bound in heauen, &amp; whatſoeuer you ſhal looce vpon yearth ſhall alſo be looced in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Vnder
<pb facs="tcp:4584:89"/> whoſe name &amp; authoritie muſte this power be exerciſed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Vnder the name and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of our ſauior Ieſus Chriſt, alſo in the name of the whole congregacion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>After what maner and fourme?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>with all godlye feruentnes and earneſt praier vnto God. For the which cauſe alſo it muſt be done in the open congregacion beeyng aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled together, &amp; with theyr conſente.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Proue me this by the woorde of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The Lorde ſayeth in the chapiter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reherſed: whanſoeuer two or thre among you do conſente together, whatſoeuer they ſhall praye for, that ſhall be doen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them of my father in heauen. For wherſoeuer two or thre are gathered together in my name
<pb facs="tcp:4584:90"/> there am I in the middeſt amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Here the lorde maketh mencion of two or three onely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>That he doeth to confirme the greater nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſmaller.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But ſhewe me ſome ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that maketh expreſſe men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the whole congregacion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>The holye Paul wryteth thus .i. Corin. v.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>J as one that am abſent from you in bodye but yet preſent with you in ſpirite, haue already (as preſente) determined and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded (againſt him that hath committed that dede), in the name of our lorde Ieſus Chriſte and in your congregacion with my ſpirite, and with the power or authoritie of our lorde Jeſus Chriſte, to geue him euer vnto the deuill, to the confuſion and peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyng of his fleſhe, that his ſpirite may be ſafe at the daye or cummyng of the lorde Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And what is the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
<pb facs="tcp:4584:90"/> or paſtors duetie to doe in all this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>He ought in no wiſe to admit vnto the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the ſacramentes ſuche as bee excluded by the churche or by the appoynted elders, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ſuche time as they be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled therunto agayne. And be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſides that, he ought to bee as it were the mouth of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>grega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion to open and to declare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the tranſgreſſours the heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of theyr ſynnes, &amp; to moue them vnto heartie repentaunce, that they maye come out of the deuils ſnares.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But nowe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe that be ſicke, howe ſhall the miniſter ordre them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>If he perceyue that they be ſorye and repentaunte for theyr ſinnes, and are deſirous of the fauoure of God &amp; of remiſſion,
<pb facs="tcp:4584:91"/> than ought he to comfort them with ſome promyſe of grace, &amp; to preache vnto them free re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and abſolucion in the preſence of ſuche as are there by aſſiſtente, leſte peraduenture their conſcience being vexed and their ſickenes increaſed, the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked enemie preuent and enſnare them, and ſo ſeduce and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueigh them into deſperacion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Where haſt thou any exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of ſcripture for that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Our ſauiour Chriſte as ſoone as he ſawe the bedredde before hym (doubtleſſe in feare of hys ſynnes) he ſayed vnto him: <hi>My ſonne bee of good comforte thy ſynnes are forgeuen thee. And agayne to the woman that had ſynned he ſayed. Goe thy way in peace, thy fayth hath ſaued thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Haſt thou no further com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente
<pb facs="tcp:4584:91"/> of the viſitacion &amp; comfort of the ſick to be doen by the miniſters of the churche?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, the holye Apoſtle S. Iames teacheth that the praier of faythe whiche the ſeniors or elders of the churche doe make for the ſicke, ſhall help them and the lorde ſhall comforte them, &amp; yf they be in ſynne, it ſhall be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuen them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe what fruite and profite ought all this to worke in thee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Fyrſte I ought to learne hereby, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue of any manne thankefully all maner of chriſtian and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly correccion, warning, and informacion. And alſo by the verye duetie and bonde of loue truely and faythfully to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe &amp; reproue my neyghboure (whiche is euery chriſtian man)
<pb facs="tcp:4584:92"/> if I ſhal ſee him offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>why, what haſt thou to do with thy neighbour:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Forſouth foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as we are all the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres of one body. If I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> finde in my heart to ſee any to loyter and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe in his ſynne, &amp; not ſo much as to admoniſh him therof, than it may appere that there is no chriſtian loue in me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Well, what other fruit may thys doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne worke in thee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>This alſo,<note place="margin">i. Corin. v. ii. Theſ. ii.</note> that I contemne not in any wyſe the diſciplyne of bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding &amp; loocyng of the churche, but eſteme &amp; drede it reuerent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: eſchewyng and auoydynge all felowſhippe and familiaritie of ſuche as wyll not conforme themſelues vnto theſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>what ſcripture haſte thou for that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S</speaker>
               <p>Euen the woordes
<pb facs="tcp:4584:92"/> of oure ſauiour Chriſt wher he ſaieth: <hi>Jf he heare not the church or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacion, than take or repute hym as an heathen and an vnchriſtian,</hi> that is to ſay, as an infidele that is ſunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſeperate from al chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ordre and felowſhip. But yet we ought not vtterly to reiecte and to hate him in our heartes, but to praye hartily vnto God for hym that he may be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from his wickednes againe: and than with all ioyfulnes to receyue hym into all chriſten fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip agayne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Well, this is ſufficient of this article alſo. Now tell me what is thy dayly exerciſe in the ſeruice of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Morning and euening whan I ariſe or goe to bed, lykewiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore &amp; after meate, I vſe theſe prayers folowing, or ſuche like.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4584:93"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4584:93"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4584:94"/>
               <p>Fyrſte at my vpriſyng I falle doune on my knees and lyftyng vp my handes and iyes vnto heauen, I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe my ſynnes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God my heauenly father af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this maner.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="confession_of_sins">
            <head>A generall confeſſion of ſynnes to be ſayed euery morning.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Almyghtie God our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye father, I confeſſe &amp; knowlege that I am a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; a wretched ſynner, &amp; haue manifolde wayes moſte gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſlye tranſgreſſed thy moſte godly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes thorow wicked thoughtes, vngodlye luſtes, ſinfull woordes &amp; dedes, and in my whole lyfe. In ſynne am I borne and conceyued, and there is no goodneſſe in me, in aſmuche as yf thou ſhouldeſt entre into thy narowe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente
<pb facs="tcp:4584:94"/> with me, iudgyng me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng vnto the ſame, I were neuer hable to ſuffer or abyde it, but muſt nedes peryſhe and be damned for euer. So lyttle help, comfort or ſuccour is there either in me, or in any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Onely this is my comfort (o heauenly father) that thou diddeſt not ſpare thy only dere-beloued ſonne, but diddeſt geue him vp vnto the moſte bittur &amp; moſte vile &amp; ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derous death of the croſſe for me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he myght ſo pay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſom for my ſinnes, ſatiſfie thy iudgement, ſtill and pacifie thy wrathe, reconcyle me agayne vnto the, and pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chace me thy grace and fauour and euerlaſtyng lyfe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thorowe the merite of hys moſte bitter death and paſſion,
<pb facs="tcp:4584:95"/> and thorow his innocent bloud ſheadyng, I beſeche thee, o hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou wylt vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to bee gracious and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfull vnto me, to forgeue, and to pardon me all my ſynnes, to lyghten my harte with thy holy ſpirite, to renewe, confirme and ſtrengthen me, with a right and a perfite fayth, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame me in loue towarde thee, &amp; my neybour, that I may he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth with a willing, and a glad harte walk as it becu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth me, in thy moſte godly commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and ſo glorifie &amp; prayſe thee euerlaſtingly. And alſo that I maye with a free conſcience and a quiet harte in all maner of temptacions, affliccions, or neceſſyties, and euen in the very panges of deth, cry bolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:4584:95"/> and merily vnto the and ſaye: I beleue in God the father all<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myghtie, maker of heauen and earthe. And in his onely ſonne Ieſus Chriſte our lorde. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But o Lorde God heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to comforte my ſelfe in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliccion and temptacion wyth theſe articles of the chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith It is not in my power. For fayth is thy gyft: and for as muche as thou wylt be prayed vnto, and called vpon for it, I cumme vnto thee, to praye and beſeche the, bothe for that and for all my other neceſſities, euen as thy deare beloued ſonne our ſauiour Chriſte Ieſus hath hymſelfe taught vs.</p>
            <p>And from the very botome of my harte, I crye and ſaye: O
<pb facs="tcp:4584:96"/> our father whiche arte in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>This doen, I adde this prayer for the mornyng.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Mercifull lorde God hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father, I re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der moſt high laudes, prayſe, and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes vnto the, that thou haſt preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me both this nyght and all the tyme and dayes of my lyfe hitherto vnder thy proteccion, and haſt ſuffred me to lyue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll this preſente houre.</p>
            <p>And I beſeche the hartily, thou wylt voucheſafe to receyue me this daye and the reſidue of my whole lyfe from hencefurthe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy tuicion, rulyng and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernyng me with thy holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, that all maner of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of miſbelefe, infidelitie, and of carnall luſtes and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feccions,
<pb facs="tcp:4584:96"/> maye be vtterlye cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and driuen out of my harte, and that I maye be iuſtified &amp; ſaued both body and ſoule tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a right and a perfect fayth, and ſo walke in the lighte of thy mooſte godlye truthe to thy glory and prayſe, and to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and furtheraunce of my ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, thorowe Ieſus Chriſte our Lorde and ſauioure. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>Or thus more brieflye.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Mercyfull lorde God, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father, I laude and prayſe the that thou haſte pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued me this nyghte, from all perill, daunger and euyll. And I beſeche the of thy mercye to kepe &amp; preſerue me from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth likewiſe. And driue all maner of darkeneſſe oute of my hart, that the light of thy truthe
<pb facs="tcp:4584:97"/> may ſhyne before me &amp; gyde me in all my wayes: And thou wil voucheſalue alſo to kepe &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerue our moſt noble kyng with all our rulers magiſtrates, tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers, parentes, and all our frendes, thorow Ieſus Chriſte our Lorde and ſauiour. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A prayer to be ſayed at nyght goyng to bedde.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Mercifull Lord God hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father, whether we ſlepe or wake, lyue or dye, we are alwayes thyne. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beſeche the hartilye that thou wilte vouchſalue to take care and charge of me, and not to ſuffre me to peryſhe in the workes of darkeneſſe, but to kindle the lyght of thy counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce in my harte, that thy godlye knowlege maye daylye increaſe in me thorowe a ryght
<pb facs="tcp:4584:97"/> and a pure faith, and that I may alwayes be founde to walke &amp; lyue after thy wyll &amp; pleaſure thorow Ieſus Chriſt our lorde and ſauiour. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>Or thus more briefly.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Mercifull lorde God our heauenly father, I laude &amp; thanke the moſte hartily for that thou haſt ſo graciouſly kepte &amp; preſerued me this daye, beſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng the to forgeue me all my ſynnes whiche I haue commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſte the, &amp; I beſeche the to preſerue me and all men this night, from all ſnares and wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of the wicked fiende. And graunte that although our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral iyes ſhal ſlepe, yet that our hertes &amp; myndes may continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally watche &amp; wake in the, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe Ieſus Chriſte our Lorde and ſauiour. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:4584:98"/>
            <head>A prayer to be ſayed before meat.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Mercifull father, thou fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt and nouriſheſt all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of creatures, voucheſalue to nouryſhe and to refreſhe vs nowe with thy gyftes, ſo that we do not miſuſe them, but that we beyng ſtrengthned thorowe them, maye bee more hable to ſerue thee in our callyng and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion of lyfe, and to walke and lyue before the in all vertue and honeſtie: through Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde and ſauiour. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>After meate.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Mercifull Lord God, our heauenly father, we laude, prayſe and thanke thee for thy moſte holy and excellent giftes, wherwith thou haſt ſo graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlye nouryſhed and refreſhed vs: And we beſeche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heartily,
<pb facs="tcp:4584:98"/> grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that we may neuer forget thy mercyfull goodnes toward vs, but that we may caſt al our care and ſorowe vpon the only, and may alway ſeke &amp; receyue, with a perfite truſt and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, all maner of ſuſtenaunce both of bodye and ſoule, at thy handes which art the fountaine and welſpryng of all goodnes, through Ieſus Chriſte our Lorde and ſauior. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Scripture_passages">
            <head>Certaine godly leſſons for al fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full people, young and olde.</head>
            <p>HArken Iſrael, the Lorde our God is one God. Thou ſhalt loue the Lorde thy God ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly with all thy heart, with all thy ſoule, and with all thy ſtrength. All theſe woordes
<pb facs="tcp:4584:99"/> whiche I commaunde the this daye, ſhall remayne continually in thy hearte. Thou ſhalt beate them diligentlye into thy chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and thruſt them ſharplye into theyr heartes. And lette all thy communicacion &amp; talkyng bee of them, whether thou beeſt in thy houſe or goeſt abrode, whether thou goeſt to bedde or ryſeſt vppe. Thou ſhalt bynde them for a token vpon thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: And let them euermore gliſter before thy iyes. Thou ſhalt wryte them vpon thy doores and vpon thy gates.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Micheas. vi.</bibl> I will tell the, O man, what is good, and what God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of the. Namely nothyng els but that thou kepeſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and doeſt ryghteouſnes,
<pb facs="tcp:4584:99"/> and that thou applye thy ſelfe vnto all godlyneſſe and walke humbly before thy Lord God.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iaco. i.</bibl> This is the pure and vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed religion before God our father, to viſite and coumforte the wedowes &amp; the fatherleſſe, in theyr ſorowe, affliccion and miſery and for a manne to kepe hymſelfe without ſpotte before the worlde.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>i. Timo. i.</bibl> The ende and fulfyllyng of all the lawe is this, namely loue, out of a pure hearte, a good conſcience, and a perfite vnfayned fayth.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iohn. xiii.</bibl> By this ſhall all men knowe, that ye are my ſcholars, yf ye loue one an other, lyke as I haue loued you.</q>
            <pb facs="tcp:4584:100"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>i. Iohn .iii.iiii.v.</bibl> God is loue, and he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth in loue, remayneth in God, and God in hym. He that hath loue is borne of God and knoweth God. He that loueth not, he knoweth not God, for God is loue. If we loue one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, than remayneth God within vs, &amp; his loue is perfite in vs. And hereby doe we know that we are the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, and that we haue loue, yf we loue God and kepe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes. And this is his commaundemente, namely that we beleue in the name of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſte, and loue one an other.</q>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The God of all grace and mercye, ſtrengthen thee and all menne in the knowlege of his
<pb facs="tcp:4584:100"/> ſonne our ſauior Ieſus, and in the power of his heauenlye and godly ſpirite. To hym be all laude, prayſe, thankes, glory, power, rule, &amp; honor world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende. Amen.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4584:101"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in</hi> Flete-ſtrete at the ſigne of the Sunne ouer againſt the conduyte, by Edwarde Whitchurche. The .xix. daye of Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tober the yere of our Lorde. <hi>M.D.XL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>III.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4584:101"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
